<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-12-22T11:32:33+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">All things Growth | Samriddhi Consulting</title><subtitle>At Samriddhi, we love to look forward and walk into uncharted territories to bring back innovative solutions for our partner clients</subtitle><author><name>vidhi</name></author><entry><title type="html">The top 3 growth lessons to learn from 2021</title><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/top-3-growth-lessons-of-2021" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The top 3 growth lessons to learn from 2021" /><published>2021-12-21T10:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-12-21T10:30:00+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/top-3-growth-lessons-of-2021</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/top-3-growth-lessons-of-2021">&lt;p&gt;It’s December already! In many ways, I am glad the year went by so quick. What started off with a resurgence of hope and normalcy, quickly turned horrifying, but is finally ending with everyone cautiously making their way into the new normal. ‘New normal’ was the go-to phrase of last year but it is this year that we have truly started to appreciate the meaning of the phrase and its gravity on our lives. Moving on from losses, displaying courage, transcending all differences to help each other, and weaving safety into the fabric of everything we do – the year has taught us many lessons that will stay with us and become our DNA. Here are my top three lessons which will help me navigate towards growth and positivity in the new year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#resilience&quot;&gt;Resilience and the Ability to bounce back &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#innovation&quot;&gt;Innovative Problem-Solving&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#sustainability&quot;&gt;Sustainability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resilience&quot;&gt;1. Resilience &amp;amp; the ability to bounce back&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I start with this lesson because at the core of all of our existence is the ability to collect ourselves from whatever we have been through and move on. Psychologist and author &lt;a href=&quot;https://angeladuckworth.com/&quot;&gt;Angela Duckworth&lt;/a&gt; indicates Resilience as the ability to bounce back after we have struggled or failed. The key to resilience is often being able to see across the darkness and just know that there is light. No one will tell you that. It comes from deep-seated optimism, faith and self-awareness. It also needs us to be gritty – to never give up trying to work towards a better tomorrow. In many ways, this is the most important milestone as we chart our road towards growth and building a better tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;innovation&quot;&gt;2. Innovative Problem Solving&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am probably cheating a little here by clubbing two critical lessons into one! However, in my defence, this year has pushed our limits to try and solve problems we never knew existed. Vaccinating your workforce was never part of any organisational job description. With businesses returning to normalcy during the first half of the year, so many of us innovated to make sure each one of their employees – no matter how remote – was safely vaccinated. This is just one example that I’m sure resonates with many of us. Several other such case studies have proven that a straight-jacketed approach to work will not work in the future. Boundaries will have to be redefined and problems will need to be seen from an innovative lens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sustainability&quot;&gt;3. Sustainability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lesson is closest to me – personally and professionally. When we started out, at Samriddhi Consulting, we made a conscious decision to choose sustainable growth projects that were meaningful and had a long-term impact on the business. However, the post-pandemic appreciation of our environment had a deeper personal impact on me. I started seriously reading up about Sustainability and realised that it is not the same as ‘environmental-ism’! Sustainability is defined by the United Nations as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote text-center bg-light&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;development that meets the needs of the present without compromising the ability of future generations to meet their own needs&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sustainabledevelopment.un.org/content/documents/5987our-common-future.pdf&quot;&gt;The United Nations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can work across the entire spectrum of activities we are involved in – social and economic. For the longest time, we were limited by our thinking that this balance is unachievable, but sometimes a jolt is needed to make us realise that what we have been taking for granted isn’t possible anymore. Work from home proved that we could reduce our carbon footprint by travelling less. 2021 has been the year when #netzero and EarthShot became forces of action towards preserving our climate. The scarcity of fuel in Britain this year was another bolt for us to consider electric vehicles seriously. Several &lt;a href=&quot;https://interestingengineering.com/21-sustainability-innovations-that-might-just-change-the-world&quot;&gt;start-ups&lt;/a&gt; are successfully and profitably engaging in responsible businesses to create a better future. My personal commitment this year has been to reduce my carbon footprint and I started by measuring mine &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.org/en-us/get-involved/how-to-help/carbon-footprint-calculator/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. As a vegetarian, who doesn’t drive around much now, I was disappointed to find out that my carbon footprint is 5.49 tonnes of CO2e as against the global average of 4 tonnes per year. But as we say, the journey towards improvement begins with measuring!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On that note, I’m looking forward to a year when I can be conscious about my personal impact on this planet and reduce to at least 4 tonnes of CO2e by next time this year and use my resilience and innovation to get there. So much for public commitments 😊 Here’s wishing all of you a wonderful festive season as well and best wishes as we ring in a new year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Kumar</name></author><category term="Organisation_Development" /><category term="new-normal," /><category term="growth," /><category term="learning," /><category term="innovation," /><category term="sustainability" /><summary type="html">It’s December already! In many ways, I am glad the year went by so quick. What started off with a resurgence of hope and normalcy, quickly turned horrifying, but is finally ending with everyone cautiously making their way into the new normal. ‘New normal’ was the go-to phrase of last year but it is this year that we have truly started to appreciate the meaning of the phrase and its gravity on our lives. Moving on from losses, displaying courage, transcending all differences to help each other, and weaving safety into the fabric of everything we do – the year has taught us many lessons that will stay with us and become our DNA. Here are my top three lessons which will help me navigate towards growth and positivity in the new year:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/2021-growth-lessons-post.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/2021-growth-lessons-post.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The debate about returning to the office</title><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/return-to-office" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The debate about returning to the office" /><published>2021-10-29T10:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-10-29T10:30:00+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/return-to-office</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/return-to-office">&lt;p&gt;Since March 2020, organisations have been caught in a mass-scale social experiment, never seen before, never imagined! Last year, every organisation went into a massive work from home experiment, overnight. Most were unprepared and several took months to adjust. Sixteen months on, with most of us double vaccinated, the question that looms in our minds now is - whether to return to office or not. Organisational pundits have predicted a hybrid model - one that can work in a few different ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before deciding what is the best ‘return-to-work’ strategy for a particular organisation, there are several factors that need to be considered – some tangible (like productivity, cost, and employee preferences) while others not so tangible (like impact on innovation and collaboration). Let’s look at it from a three-fold perspective:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#how&quot;&gt;How work is delivered in your organisation?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#where&quot;&gt;Where are your business’ touchpoints?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#who&quot;&gt;Who is your mission-critical talent and what inspires them?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how&quot;&gt;1. How work is delivered in your organisation?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deconstruct your business model and take a bold look at which pieces can be digitised or have already been automated. The pandemic has forced most organisations to adopt a digital-first approach. If most of your suppliers, employees, and customers are technologically enabled and connected, the advantage offered by a return-to-office approach is limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having said that, digitised organisations too have a need to unplug and come face-to-face. If your business model is based on intense and ongoing research, innovation, and team brainstorming, the need for these teams to come together occasionally and safely must be catered to within your return-to-work strategy. Whether this is through periodic team meetings or a quarterly retreat – options abound!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important factor to consider here is the organisation culture. Organisation cultures, like people’s personalities, are unique and often intangible. This is where you need to have maximum conversation with team leaders and listen intently to your employees. Does your organisation display the resilience and agility needed when working remotely? Are your leaders equipped to uphold the organisation’s culture without traditional levers like face-to-face town halls or physical meetings?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reimagine your work across all functions from the lens of digitalisation, automation, culture, and adaptability to narrow down to the right mix of in-person time your teams need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where&quot;&gt;2. Where are your business’ touchpoints?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The location of your current business points of contact will have a huge impact on what kind of hybrid model you want to adopt. The approach will vary widely for an organisation that has multiple retail outlets versus one from a core manufacturing sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another factor to be considered here is how your workplace supports and enables productivity. Most organisations have reported that their employees are more productive while working from home. However, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/publication/the-effects-of-remote-work-on-collaboration-among-information-workers/&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; of 61000 Microsoft employees revealed that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote text-center bg-light&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;while productivity rose during remote work, collaboration became “more static and siloed”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/publication/the-effects-of-remote-work-on-collaboration-among-information-workers/&quot;&gt;The effects of remote work on collaboration among information workers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations need to identify their primary channels of communication – formal and informal, internal and external – and these channels ought to cover both work and non-work aspects like organisational engagement and team bonding. Some teams are immensely comfortable bonding over Slack or Teams chat while others lose tacit knowledge if they don’t meet at the water cooler. Where these conversations take place within your organisations is critical to identify and feed into your return-to-work policy too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who&quot;&gt;3. Who is your mission-critical talent and what inspires them?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main reasons organisations are rethinking the ‘how’ and ‘where’ of work in the future is because a significant population of their workforce wants to keep the flexibility. In fact, according to one EY survey,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote text-center bg-light&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;more than half of employees globally would quit their jobs if not provided post-pandemic flexibility &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ey.com/en_gl/news/2021/05/more-than-half-of-employees-globally-would-quit-their-jobs-if-not-provided-post-pandemic-flexibility-ey-survey-finds&quot;&gt;2021 EY Work Reimagined Employee Survey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this talent that you will lose from return-to-work policies is easily replaceable, the answer is clear. On the flip side, is your mission-critical hard to find where your physical offices are located? Or, have you been trying to drive an inclusion and diversity agenda for years with no luck? This is the time for you to bolster your talent strategy – make it agile and inclusive. You no longer need to be limited to one city, state, or country to find the right talent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, consider the capabilities of your team leaders and managers. How does your organisation develop talent? Is coaching a structured intervention within the organisation or do managers like to mentor their teams over a face-to-face meeting?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not the least, consider role definitions and how can the talent be built to fill those roles. For fully remote roles and hybrid roles, talent sourcing is easier but you may need to invest more behind upskilling. However, roles that are fully on-site or hybrid by exception need more investment behind talent access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Blending in-office and remote workers present organisations with new challenges. As this future of work faces us, we need to look at the larger purpose of offices and how they enable organisations and teams to support their unique cultures and brand personalities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Kumar</name></author><category term="Organisation_Development" /><category term="return" /><category term="to" /><category term="work," /><category term="organisation" /><category term="design," /><category term="new-normal," /><category term="strategy," /><category term="remote" /><category term="work" /><summary type="html">Since March 2020, organisations have been caught in a mass-scale social experiment, never seen before, never imagined! Last year, every organisation went into a massive work from home experiment, overnight. Most were unprepared and several took months to adjust. Sixteen months on, with most of us double vaccinated, the question that looms in our minds now is - whether to return to office or not. Organisational pundits have predicted a hybrid model - one that can work in a few different ways.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/return-to-work-post.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/return-to-work-post.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Unravelling Decision Fatigue and how to avoid it</title><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/decision-fatigue" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unravelling Decision Fatigue and how to avoid it" /><published>2021-10-01T10:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-10-01T10:30:00+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/decision-fatigue</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/decision-fatigue">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Is a cotton mask better than an N95 mask?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Should we buy a face shield?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Can we have friends over for a tea?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Which sanitiser is safest for our family?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past sixteen months have thrown a myriad of decisions at us – most that were unused to or had no precedent to refer to for. Add to it the ever-changing information we received every day about the virus and how to deal with it. This overload of information weighed down on our minds, clouding our decision-making abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Known as &lt;strong&gt;decision fatigue&lt;/strong&gt;, this strain on our decision-making faculties is due to mental exhaustion or being forced to go through multiple complex choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-decision-fatigue-real&quot;&gt;Is decision fatigue real?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt – decision fatigue is a real threat in this post-pandemic new normal. It’s not a new phenomenon, however. We have heard of leaders and businesspeople dressing up in similar outfits to avoid the need to make complex styling decisions every morning. Barack Obama and Mark Zuckerberg being the classic and oft-quoted examples here. The key psychological concept here being that by freeing up the brain from taking redundant or repetitive decisions, the brain can focus its decision-making capabilities on more complex circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decision making by itself, even on the best of days, is a tough skill to master. In these unprecedented circumstances, it becomes more depleted because we have no experience of taking these new decisions. What, then, is the impact on us and our decision making when faced with this barrage of questions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decision fatigue is not just a feeling of tiredness. It has a real impact on our physiology and the outcomes of our decisions. According to one study,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote text-center bg-light&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;chess grandmasters often burn up to 6,000 calories per day when participating in high-level tournaments due to the intense stress of the strategic decisions they’re making. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fastcompany.com/90677496/one-unlikely-culprit-to-burnout-youre-lack-of-laziness&quot;&gt;Why a lack of lazy behavior is increasing your burnout (fastcompany.com)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Increased brain activity is indeed a real drain on energy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, research also shows that decision fatigue affects the part of the brain associated with cognition and self-control. This implies that decision fatigue can, on the one hand, cause us to take impulse actions (like binge eating or shopping) and on the other hand, get us into analysis paralysis (like delaying important decisions). Being at either end of this spectrum can be a risky proposition and lead to poor decision outcomes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-avoid-decision-fatigue&quot;&gt;How to avoid decision fatigue?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that so many months into the pandemic, it is now possible to take control of our lives and the decisions around them, to a large extent. Some proven ways to avoid decision fatigue are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-self-awareness&quot;&gt;1. Self-awareness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing what the source of your decision fatigue is and how your brain is responding to it is the first step in helping yourself avoid it. Understand your cognitive waves like the time of the day when you take your best decisions. Flow with your natural energy instead of trying to cram your day with activities as they come. For example, as a morning person, I never leave critical decisions till the end of the day. I know they will get my depleted mind share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-simplify-or-automate-choices&quot;&gt;2. Simplify or automate choices&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learn from Obama and Zuckerberg! Clothes is an easy decision to automate. I also like to automate grocery shopping, menu planning for the week and other such mundane decisions which drain my energy otherwise. The idea is simple - pick your battles!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-have-an-ally&quot;&gt;3. Have an ally&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decision fatigue affects all of us. Rely on your allies to help you through the low stretch and vice versa. Enlist close friends and family members to flag off poor decisions when you are fatigued. Also, try delegating decisions where stakes are lower for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burnout is the enemy of good decision making. Just as self-care and health have become important parts of the modern productivity toolkit, decision strength is an element that can no longer be ignored.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Kumar</name></author><category term="Instructional_Design" /><category term="decision" /><category term="fatigue," /><category term="productivity," /><category term="new-normal," /><category term="burnout," /><category term="decision" /><category term="making" /><summary type="html">Is a cotton mask better than an N95 mask?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/decision-fatigue-post.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/decision-fatigue-post.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why is my Online Training not effective?</title><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/online-training-effectiveness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why is my Online Training not effective?" /><published>2021-09-20T10:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-09-20T10:30:00+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/online-training-effectiveness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/online-training-effectiveness">&lt;p&gt;You may ask that you have tried everything from using breakout rooms to online quizzes and fun videos to engage your learners. Why then do your learners still sit with their audio and video muted in the v-ILT sessions? Why are the learning completion metrics on your LMS still low? Why do you still have to follow up with learners to log-in and complete their learning?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer these questions, I would step back to the fundamentals of instructional design. The first step is called Training Needs Assessment (TNA). It may seem like an extremely simple place to start from, but I cannot over emphasize the importance of a good need assessment because it forms the very backbone of your program. TNA is often under-rated or limited to subjective discussion-based tools. Poor understanding of the learning objectives will inadvertently lead to poor effectiveness of the program delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;form action=&quot;https://formspree.io/f/mrgrjaoo&quot; method=&quot;POST&quot; class=&quot;card ml-4 d-none d-lg-inline-block float-lg-right&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 400px&quot;&gt;
  &lt;h3 class=&quot;card-header text-center&quot;&gt;
    Get a copy of Samriddhi TNA diagnostic tool
  &lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post550.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; media=&quot;(max-width:550px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post750.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; media=&quot;(max-width:750px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; media=&quot;(min-width:751px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post550.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; media=&quot;(max-width:550px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post750.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; media=&quot;(max-width:750px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width:751px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post.jpg&quot; style=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;card-img-top&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;card-body&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;form-group&quot;&gt;
        &lt;label for=&quot;inputEmail&quot;&gt;Email address&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;email&quot; name=&quot;email&quot; class=&quot;form-control&quot; id=&quot;inputEmail&quot; aria-describedby=&quot;emailHelp&quot; required=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;small id=&quot;emailHelp&quot; class=&quot;form-text text-muted&quot;&gt;We'll never share your email with anyone else.&lt;/small&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;form-group&quot;&gt;
        &lt;label for=&quot;fullName&quot;&gt;Full Name&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;text&quot; class=&quot;form-control&quot; id=&quot;fullName&quot; name=&quot;fullName&quot; required=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;Samriddhi Consulting is committed to protecting and respecting your privacy, and we’ll only use your personal information to administer your account and to provide the products and services you requested from us. In order to provide you the content requested, we need to store and process your personal data. If you consent to us storing your personal data for this purpose, please tick the checkbox below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;form-group form-check&quot;&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;form-check-input&quot; id=&quot;emailConsent&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;label class=&quot;form-check-label small&quot; for=&quot;emailConsent&quot; name=&quot;emailConsent&quot;&gt;Please send me the tool by email&lt;/label&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;card-footer&quot;&gt;
    &lt;button type=&quot;submit&quot; class=&quot;btn btn-primary d-block mx-auto&quot;&gt;Submit&lt;/button&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may not seem like but validating learning outcomes through a detailed need assessment is in fact the less time-consuming step, as compared to what follows! This is also because at Samriddhi, we have template-ised this crucial step, so you never miss out the finer details in conducting your TNA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;d-lg-none btn btn-outline-secondary&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#tna-form&quot;&gt;Click here to get a copy of the Samriddhi TNA Diagnostic Tool&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step after TNA is what causes most of us maximum discomfort – discerning which category your learning outcomes fall into:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knowledge dissemination, or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Skill building.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is sometimes possible to confuse between these two. Consider a training on negotiation skills – do you want your learners to understand the process of negotiation? Or do you want them to develop their own style, practice it and apply it in work situations? Now who doesn’t want the latter, right? But are we then ready to commit ourselves to achieving that learning outcome? Hence it is important to understand the trade-offs between choosing between the &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;skill&lt;/em&gt; buckets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason this is important is because &lt;em&gt;sticky&lt;/em&gt; learning is only achieved when we treat learning as a process, and not as an event. So, while an information dissemination training can fall into the first bucket and be an isolated learning event, application of skills or behaviours to workplace situations, needs significant time and effort. It is this stickiness that makes the online training truly effective and is therefore brings in the concept of &lt;em&gt;performance support&lt;/em&gt; in learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Performance-supported learning answers one question: “How does my learning program enhance the performance of my learners?” And because it is such a bottom-line driven question, measuring the effectiveness of the online training is built into the program design from a very early stage.
Consider a simple example. If a learner scores high scores on all knowledge quizzes in the program, would that count towards program effectiveness? Not so much, right? However, if the learner demonstrates that she/he can apply the learning in real life situations, the program be considered effective. The idea is to replicate the learning environment as closely as possible to the actual workplace and introduce key concepts by linking them to the learners’ pre-existing knowledge, skill or behaviour patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is what makes performance-supported learning so interesting too. It offers endless opportunities to innovate on the content, experiment with varied instructional design tools and incorporate relevant workplace-linked assessments. Some different instructional design tools we have used in the recent past are scenario-based tests, job aids, video tutorial, system simulation, feedback-based role plays, etc. These are called learning scaffolding, which supports the learner as s/he walks through the process of picking up the new skill. With subsequent steps in the learning journey, we reduce the scaffolding, giving greater confidence to the learner to apply the skills in real-life scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To summarise, make sure to run a strong training needs analysis before designing your program and use performance-supported learning to make your online programs more effective. We would love to hear more from you about your experiences and challenges in making online training effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;form action=&quot;https://formspree.io/f/mrgrjaoo&quot; method=&quot;POST&quot; class=&quot;card d-lg-none&quot; id=&quot;tna-form&quot;&gt;
  &lt;h3 class=&quot;card-header text-center&quot;&gt;
    Get a copy of Samriddhi TNA diagnostic tool
  &lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post550.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; media=&quot;(max-width:550px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post750.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; media=&quot;(max-width:750px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; media=&quot;(min-width:751px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post550.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; media=&quot;(max-width:550px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post750.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; media=&quot;(max-width:750px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width:751px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post.jpg&quot; style=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;card-img-top&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;card-body&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;form-group&quot;&gt;
        &lt;label for=&quot;inputEmail&quot;&gt;Email address&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;email&quot; name=&quot;email&quot; class=&quot;form-control&quot; id=&quot;inputEmail&quot; aria-describedby=&quot;emailHelp&quot; required=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;small id=&quot;emailHelp&quot; class=&quot;form-text text-muted&quot;&gt;We'll never share your email with anyone else.&lt;/small&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;form-group&quot;&gt;
        &lt;label for=&quot;fullName&quot;&gt;Full Name&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;text&quot; class=&quot;form-control&quot; id=&quot;fullName&quot; name=&quot;fullName&quot; required=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;Samriddhi Consulting is committed to protecting and respecting your privacy, and we’ll only use your personal information to administer your account and to provide the products and services you requested from us. In order to provide you the content requested, we need to store and process your personal data. If you consent to us storing your personal data for this purpose, please tick the checkbox below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;form-group form-check&quot;&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;form-check-input&quot; id=&quot;emailConsent&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;label class=&quot;form-check-label small&quot; for=&quot;emailConsent&quot; name=&quot;emailConsent&quot;&gt;Please send me the tool by email&lt;/label&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;card-footer&quot;&gt;
    &lt;button type=&quot;submit&quot; class=&quot;btn btn-primary d-block mx-auto&quot;&gt;Submit&lt;/button&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Kumar</name></author><category term="Instructional_Design" /><category term="learning," /><category term="training" /><category term="need" /><category term="analysis," /><category term="training" /><category term="effectiveness," /><category term="training" /><category term="retention," /><category term="performance" /><summary type="html">You may ask that you have tried everything from using breakout rooms to online quizzes and fun videos to engage your learners. Why then do your learners still sit with their audio and video muted in the v-ILT sessions? Why are the learning completion metrics on your LMS still low? Why do you still have to follow up with learners to log-in and complete their learning?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/online-training-support-post.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/online-training-support-post.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">For the love of Critical Thinking</title><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/critical-thinking" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="For the love of Critical Thinking" /><published>2021-08-30T10:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-08-30T10:30:00+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/critical-thinking</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/critical-thinking">&lt;p&gt;Ever since the pandemic has started, virtual schooling has become a part of our lives. Our son has been taking all his assessments on Microsoft Teams through Forms. Many tell me that he’s lucky to have access to these tools, and I couldn’t be more grateful for that. But as a parent, I get horrified seeing test after test in Multiple-Choice Questions (MCQs) format, dumbing down education to memorisation of answers rather than discerning of facts and articulating balanced opinions. The past 16 months of virtual schooling have me worried – not for academic loss, but the learning loss. And these are distinct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me explain what I mean with the help of a commonly used example. Have you ever come across some version of the below sentence/ words in a brain teaser or a puzzle?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote text-center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;Aoccdrnig to a rscheearch at Cmabrigde Uinervtisy, it deosn't mttaer in waht oredr the ltteers in a wrod are, the olny iprmoetnt tihng is taht the frist and lsat ltteer be at the rghit pclae.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mrc-cbu.cam.ac.uk/people/matt.davis/cmabridge/&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have, I’m sure you could identify the above-jumbled sentence as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote text-center bg-light&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;According to a researcher (sic) at Cambridge University, it doesn't matter in what order the letters in a word are, the only important thing is that the first and last letter be at the right place&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mrc-cbu.cam.ac.uk/people/matt.davis/cmabridge/&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author of the above article himself isn’t sure if this research was done at the University of Cambridge, but empirical evidence of trying out this puzzle with several members of friends and family shows that it is true to a large extent. &lt;strong&gt;Now here is the caveat, and my point about learning.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apply the same rule of retaining the first and last letters in the word, and unscramble this sentence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote text-center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;Pncaaltel gtworh fotcar in asnessemst of wmoen wtih seutspced pre-esmplacia to reudce mtrnaael miobdrtiy: a seepptd wgede cletsur renioamsdd crotonl taril&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Took much longer, right? (By the way, find the solution at the end of the article, if you didn’t solve it!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unscramble exercise is not as simple if the words are unfamiliar, for example, technical terms. The brain needs to then stop and think. It needs to search for similar words or make&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;sense of the given letters. In other words, it gets challenged. Similar to what happens to the brain when we work on a complex problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When solving complex problems, the prefrontal cortex (PFC) or the “higher” brain gets activated. This part of the brain controls higher-order functions like reflection, emotional response, cognitive flexibility, and long-term memory. One such higher-order function of the PFC is Critical Thinking, which you just applied while solving the above word scrambles. Your brain searched for similar words, efficiently drew synapses from what you’ve known, and made calculated estimates to find an answer. Like any muscle, the more you exercise your brain and stretch it to make these connections, the better it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critical thinking has emerged as one of the top five Skills of the Future according to the World Economic Forum study 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
        &lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://assets.weforum.org/editor/responsive_large_webp_UxpTkN-V3dpn8Xffg7pBWoR3vYaQYn-rRBZn4Jm837E.webp 850w, https://assets.weforum.org/editor/responsive_medium_webp_KgEPcfNUGs95oW6IbPlhM9JxbCUYVrdID4Ak9hwwxvA.webp 640w, https://assets.weforum.org/editor/responsive_small_webp_70czvZKf91-2f89_Q6owpFv3p9s0c04R3h0P1aqlzYg.webp 320w&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; class=&quot;figure-img img-fluid&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; data-src=&quot;https://assets.weforum.org/editor/jTIHAAN_zfBXE8uqiGcqCCo2JfFQ2w24SKLiFkSlf0I.JPG&quot; data-srcset=&quot;https://assets.weforum.org/editor/responsive_large_TLpLhxaZzpFTD9YfFZ3sv66PFKI-6DYdGpMelqk8ZSw.JPG 850w, https://assets.weforum.org/editor/responsive_medium_TIT2qLgJ3D2i8B7xVYOKsarZyo6FHV6bQwM94_sPssw.JPG 640w, https://assets.weforum.org/editor/responsive_small_ygL6tQlha7acfnjbpjszsQB6t72QU6Jer_THjqi91fA.JPG 320w&quot; data-sizes=&quot;100vw&quot; sizes=&quot;100vw&quot; srcset=&quot;https://assets.weforum.org/editor/responsive_large_TLpLhxaZzpFTD9YfFZ3sv66PFKI-6DYdGpMelqk8ZSw.JPG 850w, https://assets.weforum.org/editor/responsive_medium_TIT2qLgJ3D2i8B7xVYOKsarZyo6FHV6bQwM94_sPssw.JPG 640w, https://assets.weforum.org/editor/responsive_small_ygL6tQlha7acfnjbpjszsQB6t72QU6Jer_THjqi91fA.JPG 320w&quot; src=&quot;https://assets.weforum.org/editor/jTIHAAN_zfBXE8uqiGcqCCo2JfFQ2w24SKLiFkSlf0I.JPG&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption text-right&quot;&gt; These are the top 10 skills for 2025. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2020/10/top-10-work-skills-of-tomorrow-how-long-it-takes-to-learn-them/&quot;&gt;World Economic Forum&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the OECD ‘Skills for 2030’ Concept Note&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote text-center bg-light&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;Critical thinking includes inductive and deductive reasoning, making correct analyses, inferences and evaluations&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oecd.org/education/2030-project/teaching-and-learning/learning/skills/Skills_for_2030_concept_note.pdf&quot;&gt;Facione et al., 1995&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the workplace, Critical Thinking refers to the ability to logically break down a complex problem, without either getting overwhelmed by it or getting bogged down into details. At Samriddhi, we call this the “agility to zoom in and zoom out”. Critical thinking needs a person to look at a problem from a solutioning perspective and be creative about the solution. As a workplace competency, you may find that it overlaps with several other competencies like emotional intelligence, data analysis, analytical thinking, and clear communication – clearly articulating the thought process, asking the right questions, and analysing information without biases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this is what makes it a little harder to develop. It is a nuanced and complex skill, which requires technique, persistent effort, and practice. In an age of information overload, we need to constantly keep filtering out incorrect data and gather relevant information, interpret and analyse it, evaluate arguments, recognise unstated assumptions, and make decisions. Fortunately, there are proven techniques that can help build critical thinking. Removing unconscious biases while interpreting information is key to thinking clearly. (View Samriddhi Consulting’s &lt;a href=&quot;/organisation_development/cognitive_biases_primer&quot;&gt;Cognitive Biases Primer&lt;/a&gt;, if you missed attending our Diversity workshop). Another useful technique for building critical thinking is Appreciative Inquiry and asking effective questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more these techniques are practiced and the sooner they are introduced, the more they become a part of one’s a natural thinking process. Circling back to where I started this blog post, it is this learning loss or lack of skill-building that I will continue to worry about during this virtual schooling experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote text-center &quot;&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;Placental growth factor in assessment of women with suspected pre-eclampsia to reduce maternal morbidity: a stepped wedge cluster randomised control trial&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Kumar</name></author><category term="Instructional_Design" /><category term="learning," /><category term="critical" /><category term="thinking" /><category term=",skills" /><category term="of" /><category term="the" /><category term="future," /><category term="workplace," /><category term="competencies" /><summary type="html">Ever since the pandemic has started, virtual schooling has become a part of our lives. Our son has been taking all his assessments on Microsoft Teams through Forms. Many tell me that he’s lucky to have access to these tools, and I couldn’t be more grateful for that. But as a parent, I get horrified seeing test after test in Multiple-Choice Questions (MCQs) format, dumbing down education to memorisation of answers rather than discerning of facts and articulating balanced opinions. The past 16 months of virtual schooling have me worried – not for academic loss, but the learning loss. And these are distinct.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/critical-thinking-post.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/critical-thinking-post.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Olympics and the value of initiative</title><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/olympics-initiative" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Olympics and the value of initiative" /><published>2021-08-11T10:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-08-11T10:30:00+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/olympics-initiative</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/olympics-initiative">&lt;p&gt;As the Tokyo Olympics draws to a close, it leaves me inspired and awed. For multiple reasons! On a personal note, for the first time, I was able to introduce my son - now eleven - to the glory of the world’s largest sporting event! Five years ago, he was too young to appreciate the grandeur of this event, all that goes into its planning (especially this unprecedented one), the training the athletes go through, the wide range of sporting events that it supports (BMX is his favourite by the way!!) and the diversity of nations that participate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not a sporting fan, as I’ve shared earlier. However, the beauty of these events is in what it teaches us beyond the sporting techniques. It warmed my heart to see Naomi Osaka light the Olympic flame, which passed through the deserving hands of so many young and old athletes, frontline workers, and school students. A perfect example of inclusion when we are planning any event as an organisation. I was immediately reminded of my first manager who would always insist that any HR intervention we plan must reach the last mile of the organisation and truly resonate with every member.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sporting events were a delight to watch even for those of us who don’t follow the sport on a regular basis. We spent an entire Sunday afternoon watching archery qualifiers and cheered for Atanu Das and Deepika Kumari!! How did that event engage me so deeply, I wondered later? I zeroed it down to two factors. One, the sheer passion of the athletes was so infectious that it permeated through the screen and had me invested in their matches. I geekily identified the second factor though as an instructional design strategy. A bite-sized video explaining every sport that helped bring viewers like me up to speed. In a matter of 60 seconds, the fast-paced video showed us the rules, the tricks, and the skills to appreciate in the sport. Voila! It was the perfect &lt;a href=&quot;/instructional_design/jitl&quot;&gt;Just-in-Time Learning&lt;/a&gt; session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, how can any thoughts on Tokyo 2020 be complete without a reference to the seven medals that India won in the Olympics and the four we won in the less talked about Paralympics? These may seem like a minuscule number in front of the top countries on the tally chart, but this Olympics was not about just winning a medal for those athletes. It was about showing unprecedented levels of grit and resilience, about patience and hard work, about relentless practice without access to comparable facilities. These medals are about ‘despite’ rather than ‘because of’ and taking the first step in the direction of winning - initiating. Mirabai’s humble abode, Ravi Dahiya’s simple village, Neeraj Chopra’s spartan training grounds - all may pale in comparison to where the top Olympians come from. However, instead of feeling victimised, these athletes took control of their passion and charged through the barriers between their skill and their achievements, and the future belongs to those of us who have taken charge of ourselves. They recognised their talent, took responsibility for training themselves, and stayed engaged in this uphill road to the medal. Even the Indian women’s hockey team that missed the medal by a whisker, has many inspiring stories to share of how they began their journey to the semi-finals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my last blog post, I referred to the fact that learning and development of an employee is no longer the onus of the organisation or HR. It is for the employee to take charge of her/ his development, or face redundancy in this rapidly changing economy. As the world of work around us changes in ways we have never imagined, we cannot afford to stick to the old ways and depend on others for our growth, wellbeing and success. This is the time when we need to take charge of what we want to learn, how we want to learn it and when. While workplaces have been significantly disrupted because of the pandemic, what has emerged from this disruption is also a freedom to delink work from time and geography. It has given room for every employee to curate individual learning journeys and roadmaps that will meet her/ his unique career aspirations and work to her/ his individual strengths and opportunities – just like our Olympians this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tokyo 2020 has taught us a lot, but my biggest takeaway is the value of taking initiative and not depending on anyone else to train, to engage or to be gritty. Till Paris ’24!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Kumar</name></author><category term="Instructional_Design" /><category term="tokyo" /><category term="olympics," /><category term="initiative," /><category term="inclusion," /><category term="workplace," /><category term="learning" /><category term="andd" /><category term="evelopment," /><category term="just-in-time" /><category term="learning," /><category term="self-learning" /><summary type="html">As the Tokyo Olympics draws to a close, it leaves me inspired and awed. For multiple reasons! On a personal note, for the first time, I was able to introduce my son - now eleven - to the glory of the world’s largest sporting event! Five years ago, he was too young to appreciate the grandeur of this event, all that goes into its planning (especially this unprecedented one), the training the athletes go through, the wide range of sporting events that it supports (BMX is his favourite by the way!!) and the diversity of nations that participate.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/olympics-initiative-post.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/olympics-initiative-post.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Trust in the new normal</title><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/trust-new-normal" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trust in the new normal" /><published>2021-07-29T10:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-07-29T10:30:00+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/trust-new-normal</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/trust-new-normal">&lt;p&gt;Has it ever happened to you that you start thinking about or reading a particular topic and then every discussion that you have leads up to the same topic? The more you read and deliberate over a particular subject, the more interesting it keeps getting. More branches keep emerging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something similar happened to me when I wrote my blog post on Naomi Osaka and vulnerability a few weeks back. One thing led to another, and I can’t stop thinking about how the constructs of vulnerability and trust intermingle at workplace – from leadership to now my latest muse, how does it manifest in the new normal remote workplace?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an independent consultant, I started working from home in late 2019 – much before the pandemic struck. Even before that, I was fortunate to have worked in a culture that encouraged flexibility and trusted me to deliver outcomes – not clock hours! So, when the lockdown first started, I heard several of my friends and associates share horror tales of being in front of the laptop camera for 9 hours, having to deliver daily reports of how they have used their day (some subtly but mostly not), keeping their teams busy with meaningless work because otherwise they don’t know how else to show productivity and worse – being micromanaged using time-sheet tools!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My mixed emotions of gratitude for not being in their situation and despair for not being able to help, got me thinking about the reasons behind such behaviours. I also did a few webinars on working in the new normal, but frustratingly most of the questions by participants were around ‘monitoring’ employees. With time, employers and employees started accepting that this was how things were going to be, but every time there is a dip in the pandemic and the lockdown is eased, employees are called back into work. You’re probably nodding your head right now as you’re reading this, if you’re one of those back at work – all masked up and stocked with sanitisers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if you’re a factory supervisor or a sales manager, I get it that your work requires you to be on field. However, if a corporate staff member is asked to work from office on a regular basis, I sense that there is a trust deficit in the organisational culture. Trust itself is a complex paradigm. Layer it up with the complexities of the pandemic and it becomes truly hard to comprehend. However, I am attempting to see trust in the new normal from the following three dimensions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Care&lt;/strong&gt;: The cornerstone of any relationship during these unprecedented times, I would place authentic and genuine care about your team members ahead of any other thought. The keyword being authentic, of course!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Competence&lt;/strong&gt;: I would have normally put this first, but these are tough times. Even then, competence cannot be traded for any other trait at work. If an employee is struggling to deliver, to understand what is expected of her/ him, is unable to ask the right questions and seek help when needed, is finding it difficult to use the empowerment provided – then I would be reluctant to trust such a team member. This is especially true of a time when I cannot see where s/he is struggling and s/he isn’t able to articulate it well enough, even if I can take time out to coach the employee. Being remote puts the onus of development and competence building on the employee – and that’s an interesting topic for my next blog post hopefully😊&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Communication&lt;/strong&gt;: I cannot over-emphasise the importance of this dimension. From being extremely clear in the goals and expectations of an employee to establishing a cadence for check-ins and reviews to finally, providing constructive and timely feedback to the employee, communication is the spine that runs all along a remote work environment. Moreover, do you really think that in a virtual setting, our erstwhile communication principles of ‘70% efficacy comes from body language’ will still hold ground? Words have become so important – and hence it is critical we communicate clearly, with simple words and confirm that the other person has understood our message. Assuming that the person on the other side of the laptop screen has read your defensive body language or the sad eye expression is setting you up for major surprises!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot being written and discussed about how workplace relationships are changing in the new normal. Trust is just one building block of organisational culture that is undergoing major flux. Data security, organisational policies, and business models are some of the others. All of these inter-mingle and have a lot to do with how trust manifests in an organisation to define what shape its culture will take when the dust settles on this pandemic. Let’s hope it’s a shape that enables us all to bring our best to work.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Kumar</name></author><category term="organisation_development" /><summary type="html">Has it ever happened to you that you start thinking about or reading a particular topic and then every discussion that you have leads up to the same topic? The more you read and deliberate over a particular subject, the more interesting it keeps getting. More branches keep emerging.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/trust-new-normal-post.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/trust-new-normal-post.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Vulnerability and trust</title><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/vulnerability-trust" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vulnerability and trust" /><published>2021-06-28T10:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-06-28T10:30:00+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/vulnerability-trust</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/vulnerability-trust">&lt;p&gt;Satya read my last blog post and in his usual style, pointed me in the direction of thinking deeper about a related topic. Rightly so, in fact. My last post on vulnerability asked tons of questions – those I don’t have answers to today and those which will only be answered as we grow as a society. But what Satya highlighted was the importance of understanding a subject we have answers to and is impacting us today - how vulnerability interlinks with trust at workplaces, and its various manifestations, especially in leader-follower relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This got me onto an exciting research spree on this vast topic. Up until last year, I had only studied the works of the brilliant Brene Brown, when it came to vulnerability and courage. I had read Paul Zak and how the neuroscience of Trust impacts workplace productivity. However, to understand how the two subjects mingle, I dug deeper into the studies by Jeff Polzer, Daniel Coyle, Roger Mayer, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A poignant research by Nienaber et al. in 2015 (Vulnerability and trust in Leader-Follower relationships) pointed out that “In the case of trust between leader and followers, both Mayer et al. (1995) and Rousseau et al. (1998) define trust as the follower’s willingness to be vulnerable based on positive expectations that his leader will not take advantage of this vulnerability.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s spare you the academic research for a moment (although if you’re a research bug like me, would love to share notes!!). I’ll, however, get to the point that intrigued me most, in all these studies - Vulnerability precedes Trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polzer’s classic Vulnerability Loop is a simple yet profound structure to explain this. I send you a signal of vulnerability. You detect it and respond with your signal of vulnerability, thereby establishing a norm in this relationship - which in turn builds trust. Think about all the relationships where there is deep trust - the vulnerability loop makes so much sense, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here’s where I’d throw a spanner - what happens when the other party - say, a leader - does not respond with vulnerability, or worse, takes advantage of your vulnerability? Would you still precede your trust with vulnerability? Would you take a leap of faith the next time you are faced with a similar situation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sure, most of us have been faced with such a situation in the past at our workplace, and our reactions would have been different. Some of us coil up in defence while others brush off the dust and take our position at the start of the vulnerability loop again! Some days we have the courage to face this lack of trust and other days, we just run out of steam. Some people, we find easier to start all over with, while with others, an irreparable breach of trust builds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these responses are so natural and human, and none can be defined as right or wrong. However, if there’s one thing that I have learnt from all this research as well as my personal brushes with vulnerability, it is the importance of starting over with a fresh slate. The importance of keeping faith and not letting past breaches of trust impact our future relationships. One may think it may be easier for leaders than followers - but speak to the managers who have stood up for their teams, only to find them unwilling to reciprocate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leader-follower relationships, like any dyadic relationship, are complex and multi-layered. A trusting one takes time and concerted effort to build and nurture, but once established, it becomes valuable beyond measure. You just have to keep looking for the right one to invest in – and that requires you to keep picking yourself up and having the courage to ‘precede with vulnerability’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one can summarise this better than my favourite Brene Brown, so I’ll leave it to her:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote bg-light p-2&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;text-center&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;I want to be in the arena.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;I want to be brave with my life.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;And when we make the choice to dare greatly, we sign up to get our asses kicked.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;We can choose courage or we can choose comfort, but we can’t have both.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer text-right&quot;&gt;Brene Brown &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.in/books/about/Rising_Strong.html?id=b4Y9tAEACAAJ&amp;amp;source=kp_book_description&amp;amp;redir_esc=y&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;&lt;cite title=&quot;Source Title&quot;&gt;Rising Strong&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Kumar</name></author><category term="organisation_development" /><summary type="html">Satya read my last blog post and in his usual style, pointed me in the direction of thinking deeper about a related topic. Rightly so, in fact. My last post on vulnerability asked tons of questions – those I don’t have answers to today and those which will only be answered as we grow as a society. But what Satya highlighted was the importance of understanding a subject we have answers to and is impacting us today - how vulnerability interlinks with trust at workplaces, and its various manifestations, especially in leader-follower relationships. This got me onto an exciting research spree on this vast topic. Up until last year, I had only studied the works of the brilliant Brene Brown, when it came to vulnerability and courage. I had read Paul Zak and how the neuroscience of Trust impacts workplace productivity. However, to understand how the two subjects mingle, I dug deeper into the studies by Jeff Polzer, Daniel Coyle, Roger Mayer, and more. A poignant research by Nienaber et al. in 2015 (Vulnerability and trust in Leader-Follower relationships) pointed out that “In the case of trust between leader and followers, both Mayer et al. (1995) and Rousseau et al. (1998) define trust as the follower’s willingness to be vulnerable based on positive expectations that his leader will not take advantage of this vulnerability.” Let’s spare you the academic research for a moment (although if you’re a research bug like me, would love to share notes!!). I’ll, however, get to the point that intrigued me most, in all these studies - Vulnerability precedes Trust. Polzer’s classic Vulnerability Loop is a simple yet profound structure to explain this. I send you a signal of vulnerability. You detect it and respond with your signal of vulnerability, thereby establishing a norm in this relationship - which in turn builds trust. Think about all the relationships where there is deep trust - the vulnerability loop makes so much sense, right? But here’s where I’d throw a spanner - what happens when the other party - say, a leader - does not respond with vulnerability, or worse, takes advantage of your vulnerability? Would you still precede your trust with vulnerability? Would you take a leap of faith the next time you are faced with a similar situation? I am sure, most of us have been faced with such a situation in the past at our workplace, and our reactions would have been different. Some of us coil up in defence while others brush off the dust and take our position at the start of the vulnerability loop again! Some days we have the courage to face this lack of trust and other days, we just run out of steam. Some people, we find easier to start all over with, while with others, an irreparable breach of trust builds. All these responses are so natural and human, and none can be defined as right or wrong. However, if there’s one thing that I have learnt from all this research as well as my personal brushes with vulnerability, it is the importance of starting over with a fresh slate. The importance of keeping faith and not letting past breaches of trust impact our future relationships. One may think it may be easier for leaders than followers - but speak to the managers who have stood up for their teams, only to find them unwilling to reciprocate. Leader-follower relationships, like any dyadic relationship, are complex and multi-layered. A trusting one takes time and concerted effort to build and nurture, but once established, it becomes valuable beyond measure. You just have to keep looking for the right one to invest in – and that requires you to keep picking yourself up and having the courage to ‘precede with vulnerability’. No one can summarise this better than my favourite Brene Brown, so I’ll leave it to her:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/vulnerability-trust-post.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/vulnerability-trust-post.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Being Vulnerable</title><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/being-vulnerable" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Being Vulnerable" /><published>2021-06-03T10:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-06-03T10:30:00+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/being-vulnerable</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/being-vulnerable">&lt;p&gt;I am writing after an extraordinarily long time. I couldn’t get myself to…amidst the disturbing second wave of the pandemic in India. The losses of those so dear to me like my mentor and my best friend’s father felt too painful to recover from. But this post isn’t about the negativity, it’s about emerging from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the worst hopefully behind us, I took to reading some of the more positive pieces of news. The most striking one in recent days that encouraged me to write, was the uplifting news of Naomi Osaka. The 23-years old tennis superstar has shocked the sports world by announcing that she will withdraw from this year’s French Open. It all started when she announced that she wouldn’t participate in any post-game press conferences. According to this emotionally intelligent athlete, these press conferences only kicked down the loser, at a time when s/he was already at a low. That made so much sense to me… Refreshingly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the leaders of the world’s top tennis organisations pointed out to the Code of Conduct that she will be breaching by doing so, while in the same piece assuring that they were concerned about Osaka’s wellbeing. Unsurprisingly, the double standards were visible to more than just Osaka.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;News like this stands out in our faces not because they are rocking the world of tennis alone, but also because they show that a new era of role models is emerging. Is this really an unveiling of the responsible celebrities, who care as much for their mental health as for their physical fitness? More importantly, is a section of the next generation finally finding their deep-seated vulnerability and courage, to stand up for what feels right to them, rather than cow down to legal arm twisting or social pressures? Athletes from even a decade older would push their boundaries and hurt themselves to show their invincibilities. What it did to their mental and emotional well-being was a question never asked. Who wants to look soft and mushy on the court, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take it to the corporate and you will find the same parallels. No one wants to look emotionally vulnerable in a job, let alone talk about it. We continue to drag on our steely persona, to a point that we sometimes forget the inner voice that’s asking for help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Osaka’s news comes as huge learning in emotional intelligence, vulnerability and courage for leaders today. As employees grapple with so much at a personal level, can we give them room to bring their vulnerable selves to work? Can we accept them when they say, “I’m not okay to do this right now” or, “I think I need to step back and take care of my mental well-being”? How do leaders role model this behaviour - by putting up their steely front or by accepting that they are not beyond shock and loss? How do corporate cultures support those who bring up their needs for mental help?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vulnerability is the cornerstone of a brave and kind corporate culture, one that allows people to fight their battles, but also empathise when they can’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes courage to build such a culture - and Osaka’s news had given me hope that as the world of sports evolves to make way for a new form of strength, the corporate leaders will also explore the place of vulnerability and empathy in their businesses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Kumar</name></author><category term="organisation_development" /><summary type="html">I am writing after an extraordinarily long time. I couldn’t get myself to…amidst the disturbing second wave of the pandemic in India. The losses of those so dear to me like my mentor and my best friend’s father felt too painful to recover from. But this post isn’t about the negativity, it’s about emerging from it.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/naomi_osaka-post.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/naomi_osaka-post.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Putting Universal Design for Learning into Action</title><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/putting-universal-design-for-learning-into-action" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Putting Universal Design for Learning into Action" /><published>2021-04-15T10:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-04-15T10:30:00+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/putting-universal-design-for-learning-into-action</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/putting-universal-design-for-learning-into-action">&lt;p&gt;In this three-part blog post series, I have shared some of my reasons for using UDL principles in my instruction design. If that’s interested you so far, you will certainly find this last post helpful in a more practical and hands-on way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me begin by asking this – what’s the first thing you would do if you had to design a training program around a given set of training needs? Most training and development professionals I meet start by opening their MS PowerPoint or equivalent tool. What follows then is a traditional course requiring students to attend the ILT/ v-ILT, read specific texts, and then take a quiz or assessment at the end of the course to demonstrate their understanding. The outcome of such a program is content that leans more towards the style of the course creator, rather than being universal in its access and approach, like we discussed in the first blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do you start applying UDL? I start by addressing the three key components of UDL in the course design by asking –&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Affective Network: Can I engage my students in active learning and encourage them to see the value in content knowledge?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recognition Network: Can I offer a variety of materials or paths in order to learn content to achieve each outcome?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Strategic Network: Can I offer multiple means of representation and expression for each learning outcome?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This helps me plot the different options I can design for recruiting and maintaining interest in the course, organising and learning new knowledge or skill, and communicating or expressing that acquired skill. Some of you may rightly find this similar to Bloom’s Taxonomy. Indeed, the questions asked at varying levels of complexity makes it possible to include the greatest number of students, and also helps to make the subject matter more engaging for everyone. In fact, Bloom’s Taxonomy compliments the principles of Universal Design for Learning because it allows students to learn about the same content at varying levels of complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now having answered the above three questions, what are some of these design options or strategies you can use for ensuring each of the UDL principles of engagement, representation and motivation? Here are some of my favourite actionable steps that I take to target each of the three networks while designing an inclusive program:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Addressing the Affective network or the ‘why’ of learning
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Share clear outcomes or learning goals at the start of the course&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Provide adequate resources like pre-reads to prime the learners&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support learning with stimulating activities&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Build a collaborative community to support learners, including discussion forums, Q&amp;amp;A board&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Encourage a safe learning culture&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Addressing the Recognition network or the ‘what’ of learning
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Understand and call out learner differences during the design phase&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Clarify the terminology used; perhaps include a glossary, especially for technical trainings&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Maximise use of scaffolding techniques when introducing new skill&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Illustrate the learning content using a variety of media&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Addressing the Strategic network or the ‘how’ of learning
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reach the learner through a variety of mechanisms&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Build in a rhythm around the learning process (for eg. goal setting, monitoring, reflection)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Provide a variety of learning tools like journals, videos, podcasts&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Give ample practice opportunities to support fluency of skills&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Monitor application of skills&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are of course just a set of techniques that have held me in good stead while designing accessible and inclusive learning content. Feel free to apply these in your own context. Hope you enjoyed this blog post series. Look forward to hearing from you about your thoughts about inclusive learning and your experiments with UDL.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Kumar</name></author><category term="Instructional_Design" /><summary type="html">In this three-part blog post series, I have shared some of my reasons for using UDL principles in my instruction design. If that’s interested you so far, you will certainly find this last post helpful in a more practical and hands-on way.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/udl_lego_blocks-post.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/udl_lego_blocks-post.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>