<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>All things Growth | Samriddhi Consulting</title>
    <description>At Samriddhi, we love to look forward and walk into uncharted territories to bring back innovative solutions for our partner clients</description>
    <link>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 12:49:30 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 12:49:30 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Vulnerability and trust</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Satya read my last blog post and in his usual style, pointed me in the direction of thinking deeper about a related topic. Rightly so, in fact. My last post on vulnerability asked tons of questions – those I don’t have answers to today and those which will only be answered as we grow as a society. But what Satya highlighted was the importance of understanding a subject we have answers to and is impacting us today - how vulnerability interlinks with trust at workplaces, and its various manifestations, especially in leader-follower relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This got me onto an exciting research spree on this vast topic. Up until last year, I had only studied the works of the brilliant Brene Brown, when it came to vulnerability and courage. I had read Paul Zak and how the neuroscience of Trust impacts workplace productivity. However, to understand how the two subjects mingle, I dug deeper into the studies by Jeff Polzer, Daniel Coyle, Roger Mayer, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A poignant research by Nienaber et al. in 2015 (Vulnerability and trust in Leader-Follower relationships) pointed out that “In the case of trust between leader and followers, both Mayer et al. (1995) and Rousseau et al. (1998) define trust as the follower’s willingness to be vulnerable based on positive expectations that his leader will not take advantage of this vulnerability.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s spare you the academic research for a moment (although if you’re a research bug like me, would love to share notes!!). I’ll, however, get to the point that intrigued me most, in all these studies - Vulnerability precedes Trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polzer’s classic Vulnerability Loop is a simple yet profound structure to explain this. I send you a signal of vulnerability. You detect it and respond with your signal of vulnerability, thereby establishing a norm in this relationship - which in turn builds trust. Think about all the relationships where there is deep trust - the vulnerability loop makes so much sense, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here’s where I’d throw a spanner - what happens when the other party - say, a leader - does not respond with vulnerability, or worse, takes advantage of your vulnerability? Would you still precede your trust with vulnerability? Would you take a leap of faith the next time you are faced with a similar situation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sure, most of us have been faced with such a situation in the past at our workplace, and our reactions would have been different. Some of us coil up in defence while others brush off the dust and take our position at the start of the vulnerability loop again! Some days we have the courage to face this lack of trust and other days, we just run out of steam. Some people, we find easier to start all over with, while with others, an irreparable breach of trust builds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these responses are so natural and human, and none can be defined as right or wrong. However, if there’s one thing that I have learnt from all this research as well as my personal brushes with vulnerability, it is the importance of starting over with a fresh slate. The importance of keeping faith and not letting past breaches of trust impact our future relationships. One may think it may be easier for leaders than followers - but speak to the managers who have stood up for their teams, only to find them unwilling to reciprocate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leader-follower relationships, like any dyadic relationship, are complex and multi-layered. A trusting one takes time and concerted effort to build and nurture, but once established, it becomes valuable beyond measure. You just have to keep looking for the right one to invest in – and that requires you to keep picking yourself up and having the courage to ‘precede with vulnerability’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one can summarise this better than my favourite Brene Brown, so I’ll leave it to her:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote bg-light p-2&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;text-center&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;I want to be in the arena.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;I want to be brave with my life.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;And when we make the choice to dare greatly, we sign up to get our asses kicked.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;We can choose courage or we can choose comfort, but we can’t have both.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer text-right&quot;&gt;Brene Brown &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.in/books/about/Rising_Strong.html?id=b4Y9tAEACAAJ&amp;amp;source=kp_book_description&amp;amp;redir_esc=y&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;&lt;cite title=&quot;Source Title&quot;&gt;Rising Strong&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jun 2021 10:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/vulnerability-trust</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/vulnerability-trust</guid>
        
        
        <category>organisation_development</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Being Vulnerable</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I am writing after an extraordinarily long time. I couldn’t get myself to…amidst the disturbing second wave of the pandemic in India. The losses of those so dear to me like my mentor and my best friend’s father felt too painful to recover from. But this post isn’t about the negativity, it’s about emerging from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the worst hopefully behind us, I took to reading some of the more positive pieces of news. The most striking one in recent days that encouraged me to write, was the uplifting news of Naomi Osaka. The 23-years old tennis superstar has shocked the sports world by announcing that she will withdraw from this year’s French Open. It all started when she announced that she wouldn’t participate in any post-game press conferences. According to this emotionally intelligent athlete, these press conferences only kicked down the loser, at a time when s/he was already at a low. That made so much sense to me… Refreshingly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the leaders of the world’s top tennis organisations pointed out to the Code of Conduct that she will be breaching by doing so, while in the same piece assuring that they were concerned about Osaka’s wellbeing. Unsurprisingly, the double standards were visible to more than just Osaka.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;News like this stands out in our faces not because they are rocking the world of tennis alone, but also because they show that a new era of role models is emerging. Is this really an unveiling of the responsible celebrities, who care as much for their mental health as for their physical fitness? More importantly, is a section of the next generation finally finding their deep-seated vulnerability and courage, to stand up for what feels right to them, rather than cow down to legal arm twisting or social pressures? Athletes from even a decade older would push their boundaries and hurt themselves to show their invincibilities. What it did to their mental and emotional well-being was a question never asked. Who wants to look soft and mushy on the court, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take it to the corporate and you will find the same parallels. No one wants to look emotionally vulnerable in a job, let alone talk about it. We continue to drag on our steely persona, to a point that we sometimes forget the inner voice that’s asking for help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Osaka’s news comes as huge learning in emotional intelligence, vulnerability and courage for leaders today. As employees grapple with so much at a personal level, can we give them room to bring their vulnerable selves to work? Can we accept them when they say, “I’m not okay to do this right now” or, “I think I need to step back and take care of my mental well-being”? How do leaders role model this behaviour - by putting up their steely front or by accepting that they are not beyond shock and loss? How do corporate cultures support those who bring up their needs for mental help?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vulnerability is the cornerstone of a brave and kind corporate culture, one that allows people to fight their battles, but also empathise when they can’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes courage to build such a culture - and Osaka’s news had given me hope that as the world of sports evolves to make way for a new form of strength, the corporate leaders will also explore the place of vulnerability and empathy in their businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 10:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/being-vulnerable</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/being-vulnerable</guid>
        
        
        <category>organisation_development</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Putting Universal Design for Learning into Action</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this three-part blog post series, I have shared some of my reasons for using UDL principles in my instruction design. If that’s interested you so far, you will certainly find this last post helpful in a more practical and hands-on way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me begin by asking this – what’s the first thing you would do if you had to design a training program around a given set of training needs? Most training and development professionals I meet start by opening their MS PowerPoint or equivalent tool. What follows then is a traditional course requiring students to attend the ILT/ v-ILT, read specific texts, and then take a quiz or assessment at the end of the course to demonstrate their understanding. The outcome of such a program is content that leans more towards the style of the course creator, rather than being universal in its access and approach, like we discussed in the first blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do you start applying UDL? I start by addressing the three key components of UDL in the course design by asking –&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Affective Network: Can I engage my students in active learning and encourage them to see the value in content knowledge?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recognition Network: Can I offer a variety of materials or paths in order to learn content to achieve each outcome?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Strategic Network: Can I offer multiple means of representation and expression for each learning outcome?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This helps me plot the different options I can design for recruiting and maintaining interest in the course, organising and learning new knowledge or skill, and communicating or expressing that acquired skill. Some of you may rightly find this similar to Bloom’s Taxonomy. Indeed, the questions asked at varying levels of complexity makes it possible to include the greatest number of students, and also helps to make the subject matter more engaging for everyone. In fact, Bloom’s Taxonomy compliments the principles of Universal Design for Learning because it allows students to learn about the same content at varying levels of complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now having answered the above three questions, what are some of these design options or strategies you can use for ensuring each of the UDL principles of engagement, representation and motivation? Here are some of my favourite actionable steps that I take to target each of the three networks while designing an inclusive program:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Addressing the Affective network or the ‘why’ of learning
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Share clear outcomes or learning goals at the start of the course&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Provide adequate resources like pre-reads to prime the learners&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support learning with stimulating activities&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Build a collaborative community to support learners, including discussion forums, Q&amp;amp;A board&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Encourage a safe learning culture&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Addressing the Recognition network or the ‘what’ of learning
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Understand and call out learner differences during the design phase&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Clarify the terminology used; perhaps include a glossary, especially for technical trainings&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Maximise use of scaffolding techniques when introducing new skill&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Illustrate the learning content using a variety of media&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Addressing the Strategic network or the ‘how’ of learning
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reach the learner through a variety of mechanisms&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Build in a rhythm around the learning process (for eg. goal setting, monitoring, reflection)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Provide a variety of learning tools like journals, videos, podcasts&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Give ample practice opportunities to support fluency of skills&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Monitor application of skills&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are of course just a set of techniques that have held me in good stead while designing accessible and inclusive learning content. Feel free to apply these in your own context. Hope you enjoyed this blog post series. Look forward to hearing from you about your thoughts about inclusive learning and your experiments with UDL.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2021 10:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/putting-universal-design-for-learning-into-action</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/putting-universal-design-for-learning-into-action</guid>
        
        
        <category>Instructional_Design</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Universal Design for Learning: The history and the future </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;With its roots deep into accessibility, I found it hardly surprising that the origins of Universal Design were in architecture. Ronald Mace, an American architect and product designer, coined the term Universal Design – as a means to promote the design of products and spaces that would be accessible to all people, and still meet the requirements of the Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This early version permitted a lot of flexibility to users and designers alike, and soon started to appeal to designers of classroom and other educational facilities where physical access was important. Although this helped schools include students with disabilities in a classroom, it still left a lacuna when it came to access to curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was addressed when in 1984, the Centre for Applied Special Technology or CAST was founded. Their work in developing innovative, technology-based educational resources and strategies created a need for making learning design accessible. Building on the existing work in Universal Design, CAST teamed up with developmental psychologist Lev Vygotsky who was studying the prerequisites for learning. Together they identified the three brain networks that today form the core of Universal Design for Learning or UDL:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Affective network: engagement with the learning task.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recognition network: recognition of the information to be learned.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Strategic network: application of strategies to process information.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today Universal Design principles of education have become the mainstay of some of the best educator training programs – encouraging educators how to ensure that their curriculum and learning strategies are designed to accommodate for individual differences in their learners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of UDL demonstrates the seamless cross pollination of ideas – educators drawing inspiration from architects and product designers, building on ideas to create something so succinct and profound. It – to me – is hope that this chain of symbiotic growth can continue from educators to corporate L&amp;amp;D professionals. Looking at their learners from a lens of andragogy instead of pedagogy, instructional designers can apply UDL principles to include a wider diversity in their classrooms or v-ILT sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With corporate learners seeking on-demand professional development, it will become increasingly rare to see homogenous classrooms – training sessions organised by a single organisation for a single type of audience, on a single topic. Imagine a subject like change management, which was earlier a highly rated strategy lesson – now has become relevant to every employee. Designing a curriculum that appeals to a fresh college graduate, a mid-level manager or a CEO, creating it such that the activities resound with their individual context and presenting the course keeping their demographic sensitivities in mind – these are not ‘good-to-do’s’ for an instructional designer anymore. They are very shortly going to become must-dos. Embracing the UDL framework will help us achieve inclusion of learning design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next and the last part of these blog post series dedicated to UDL, I will be sharing some of the ways we can use UDL guidelines in our context and some universal design for learning examples of my favourites!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 10:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/universal-design-for-learning-the-history-and-the-future</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/universal-design-for-learning-the-history-and-the-future</guid>
        
        
        <category>Instructional_Design</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cognitive Biases Primer</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;With their origins in the hunter-gatherer evolution of humans, cognitive biases are deeply rooted into our neuroscience​. These are mental shortcuts (known as heuristics), that help us make sense of the vast information around us​. Without them, we will be crippled when it comes to fast decision making and survival.​&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-theres-nothing-wrong-with-having-unconscious-bias-right-&quot;&gt;So there’s nothing wrong with having unconscious bias, right? ​&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not entirely!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;​Unconscious bias is great for survival and ‘fast’ decision making, as Daniel Kahneman would put it - System 1 Thinking (Thinking, Fast and Slow – 2013)​.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, ‘slow’ and deliberate thinking (System 2 Thinking) requires us to remove these filters​&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good news is – it’s possible to work-around these biases once you are aware how to spot them. Let’s look at the top 10 biases that can cloud your decision making at a workplace and how to work around them.​&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;10-types-of-cognitive-bias&quot;&gt;10 Types of Cognitive Bias:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Likeability Bias&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Affinity Bias&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attribution Bias&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Confirmation Bias&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Halo (or Horns) Effect&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Proximity Bias&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bandwagon Bias&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Loss Aversion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anchoring Bias&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Availability Heuristic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row row-cols-1 row-cols-md-2&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col mb-2&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;card text-center&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/likeability_bias-post.jpg&quot; class=&quot;card-img-top&quot; alt=&quot;A person holding a white lapel pin with a red heart drawn on it &quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;small class=&quot;m-0 p-0 pb-2&quot;&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@kellysikkema?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Kelly Sikkema&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@pranesh_n/likes?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;card-body&quot;&gt;
                &lt;h4 class=&quot;card-title&quot;&gt;Likeability Bias&lt;/h4&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;card-text&quot;&gt;Rooted in how we expect people of certain groups to behave, this bias leads us to liking people who behave as per these expectations. For example, men are liked when they are assertive, women when they are gentle and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                    &lt;h5 class=&quot;card-subtitle list-group-item border-top border-bottom-0 text-muted&quot;&gt;Manifestations at work&lt;/h5&gt;
                    &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;A woman may assert her ideas and face ‘likeability penalty’, getting her ideas shot down. &lt;/li&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;A young intern is not liked for questioning established processes and suggesting new ones&lt;/li&gt;
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                    &lt;h5 class=&quot;card-subtitle list-group-item text-muted border-top border-bottom-0&quot;&gt;Work Around&lt;/h5&gt;
                    &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Separate the person from the idea&lt;/li&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Institute standard, competency-based processes for evaluation of ideas and performance, regardless of who is assessing or being assessed&lt;/li&gt;
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                &lt;/ul&gt;    
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col mb-2&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;card text-center&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/affinity_bias-post.jpg&quot; class=&quot;card-img-top&quot; alt=&quot;Peas in a Pod&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;small class=&quot;m-0 p-0 pb-2&quot;&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@rachaelgorjestani?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Rachael Gorjestani&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@pranesh_n/likes?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;card-body&quot;&gt;
                &lt;h4 class=&quot;card-title&quot;&gt;Affinity Bias&lt;/h4&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;card-text&quot;&gt;Our tendency to gravitate towards people like ourselves in appearance, beliefs, and background. Flip side, we may avoid or even dislike people different from us.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                    &lt;h5 class=&quot;card-subtitle list-group-item border-top border-bottom-0 text-muted&quot;&gt;Manifestations at work&lt;/h5&gt;
                    &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;The classic ‘culture fit’ hiring – we are unconsciously falling for someone who reminds us of ourselves&lt;/li&gt;
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                    &lt;h5 class=&quot;card-subtitle list-group-item text-muted border-top border-bottom-0&quot;&gt;Work Around&lt;/h5&gt;
                    &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Actively take note of the similarities you share with another person so that you can differentiate between attributes that may cloud your judgement&lt;/li&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Start talking about ‘culture adds’ rather than ‘culture fits’&lt;/li&gt;
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                &lt;/ul&gt;    
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col mb-2&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;card text-center&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/attribution_bias-post.jpg&quot; class=&quot;card-img-top&quot; alt=&quot;Silhouette of a man&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;small class=&quot;m-0 p-0 pb-2&quot;&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@benjaminsweet?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Ben Sweet&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@pranesh_n/likes?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;card-body&quot;&gt;
                &lt;h4 class=&quot;card-title&quot;&gt;Attribution Bias&lt;/h4&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;card-text&quot;&gt;Attribution bias is a phenomenon where you try to make sense of or judge a person’s behavior based on prior observations and interactions you’ve had with that group represented by the individual.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                    &lt;h5 class=&quot;card-subtitle list-group-item border-top border-bottom-0 text-muted&quot;&gt;Manifestations at work&lt;/h5&gt;
                    &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Women are considered less competent at certain domains like STEM&lt;/li&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;People from vernacular backgrounds are assumed to have challenges with English speaking skills&lt;/li&gt;
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                    &lt;h5 class=&quot;card-subtitle list-group-item text-muted border-top border-bottom-0&quot;&gt;Work Around&lt;/h5&gt;
                    &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Don’t assume. Ask.&lt;/li&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Hear the full story of the person and treat them as unique&lt;/li&gt;
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                &lt;/ul&gt;    
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col mb-2&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;card text-center&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/confirmation_bias-post.jpg&quot; class=&quot;card-img-top&quot; alt=&quot;A black cat&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;small class=&quot;m-0 p-0 pb-2&quot;&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@t_ahmetler?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Tolga Ahmetler&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@pranesh_n/likes?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;card-body&quot;&gt;
                &lt;h4 class=&quot;card-title&quot;&gt;Confirmation Bias&lt;/h4&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;card-text&quot;&gt;Our tendency to favour information that confirms our pre-existing beliefs. This occurs when we have decided a course of action and look for evidence to prove it correct!&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                    &lt;h5 class=&quot;card-subtitle list-group-item border-top border-bottom-0 text-muted&quot;&gt;Manifestations at work&lt;/h5&gt;
                    &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Based on the resume, the hiring decision is made up and the interview is used to prove that decision right.&lt;/li&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;A new worker is judged a certain way and all interactions with the team make the judgment come true.&lt;/li&gt;
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                    &lt;h5 class=&quot;card-subtitle list-group-item text-muted border-top border-bottom-0&quot;&gt;Work Around&lt;/h5&gt;
                    &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Competency based hiring or using structured/ standardised interviews.&lt;/li&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Introduce a robust onboarding processes.&lt;/li&gt;
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                &lt;/ul&gt;    
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col mb-2&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;card text-center&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/halo_horns_effect-post.jpg&quot; class=&quot;card-img-top&quot; alt=&quot;Person with halo behind&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;small class=&quot;m-0 p-0 pb-2&quot;&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@asmith360?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Adrian Smith&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@pranesh_n/likes?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;card-body&quot;&gt;
                &lt;h4 class=&quot;card-title&quot;&gt;Halo (or Horns) Effect&lt;/h4&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;card-text&quot;&gt;The tendency to judge others similarly on all traits. The assumption that because someone is good or bad at one thing, they will be equally good or bad at another.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                    &lt;h5 class=&quot;card-subtitle list-group-item border-top border-bottom-0 text-muted&quot;&gt;Manifestations at work&lt;/h5&gt;
                    &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Candidates from a certain education background are treated highly or poorly.&lt;/li&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;A person who is often late to work is overlooked for promotions despite overachieving targets.&lt;/li&gt;
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                    &lt;h5 class=&quot;card-subtitle list-group-item text-muted border-top border-bottom-0&quot;&gt;Work Around&lt;/h5&gt;
                    &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Introduce multiple rounds of interviewing in the hiring process, when different people view the candidates.&lt;/li&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Set clear expectations.&lt;/li&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Hear the person.&lt;/li&gt;
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                &lt;/ul&gt;    
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col mb-2&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;card text-center&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/proximity_bias-post.jpg&quot; class=&quot;card-img-top&quot; alt=&quot;Water drops on blooms&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;small class=&quot;m-0 p-0 pb-2&quot;&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@tolga__?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Tolga Ulkan&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@pranesh_n/likes?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;card-body&quot;&gt;
                &lt;h4 class=&quot;card-title&quot;&gt;Proximity Bias&lt;/h4&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;card-text&quot;&gt;People who work in close proximity have a larger impact on our thinking and decision making than those away.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                    &lt;h5 class=&quot;card-subtitle list-group-item border-top border-bottom-0 text-muted&quot;&gt;Manifestations at work&lt;/h5&gt;
                    &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Candidates interviewed in person are viewed more favorably than those interviewed via distance technology.&lt;/li&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Remote team members receive a less favourable performance feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                    &lt;h5 class=&quot;card-subtitle list-group-item text-muted border-top border-bottom-0&quot;&gt;Work Around&lt;/h5&gt;
                    &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Level the playing field. Use the same method of communication when conducting team meetings.&lt;/li&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Use standardised/ competency-based processes.&lt;/li&gt;
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                &lt;/ul&gt;    
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col mb-2&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;card text-center&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/bandwagon_bias-post.jpg&quot; class=&quot;card-img-top&quot; alt=&quot;Hands of people at a concert raised above their head&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;small class=&quot;m-0 p-0 pb-2&quot;&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@theunsteady5?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Edwin Andrade&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@pranesh_n/likes?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;card-body&quot;&gt;
                &lt;h4 class=&quot;card-title&quot;&gt;Bandwagon Bias&lt;/h4&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;card-text&quot;&gt;A common bias favouring ideas adopted by others. It could take the shape of Conformity bias – acting similar to people around, regardless of own beliefs – or Authority bias – when linked to an influential person’s beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                    &lt;h5 class=&quot;card-subtitle list-group-item border-top border-bottom-0 text-muted&quot;&gt;Manifestations at work&lt;/h5&gt;
                    &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Ideas suggested by the team leader or majority are voted up.&lt;/li&gt;
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                    &lt;h5 class=&quot;card-subtitle list-group-item text-muted border-top border-bottom-0&quot;&gt;Work Around&lt;/h5&gt;
                    &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Gain everyone’s personal perspective separately first (either through a silent, written brainstorm or through one-on-one conversations) before opening it to the team for review and discussion.&lt;/li&gt;
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                &lt;/ul&gt;    
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col mb-2&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;card text-center&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/loss_aversion-post.jpg&quot; class=&quot;card-img-top&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of a black pug on a mattress&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;small class=&quot;m-0 p-0 pb-2&quot;&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@charlesdeluvio?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Charles Deluvio&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@pranesh_n/likes?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;card-body&quot;&gt;
                &lt;h4 class=&quot;card-title&quot;&gt;Loss Aversion&lt;/h4&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;card-text&quot;&gt;Preferring the choice that has been decided upon rather than looking for more and better options. Choosing low-risk certainty over high-risk potential.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                    &lt;h5 class=&quot;card-subtitle list-group-item border-top border-bottom-0 text-muted&quot;&gt;Manifestations at work&lt;/h5&gt;
                    &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;“This is how it’s been done”&lt;/li&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;“This solution worked the last time”&lt;/li&gt;
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                    &lt;h5 class=&quot;card-subtitle list-group-item text-muted border-top border-bottom-0&quot;&gt;Work Around&lt;/h5&gt;
                    &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;“Thou shalt not fall in love with thy solutions”&lt;/li&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Put away the tried and tested or low-risk solutions and brainstorm new ones. If you still revert to the tried and tested ones, you still got a few more ideas for next time!&lt;/li&gt;
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                &lt;/ul&gt;    
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col mb-2&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;card text-center&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/anchoring_bias-post.jpg&quot; class=&quot;card-img-top&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of a pug pulling on the handles of a bag&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;small class=&quot;m-0 p-0 pb-2&quot;&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@darisja?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Darinka Kievskaya&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@pranesh_n/likes?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;card-body&quot;&gt;
                &lt;h4 class=&quot;card-title&quot;&gt;Anchoring Bias&lt;/h4&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;card-text&quot;&gt;Being influenced by the first piece of information obtained and using it as the baseline for comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                    &lt;h5 class=&quot;card-subtitle list-group-item border-top border-bottom-0 text-muted&quot;&gt;Manifestations at work&lt;/h5&gt;
                    &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Expecting a new management trainee to behave the same way as you did when you joined your first job! &lt;/li&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Rejecting all CVs because you have ‘anchored’ your expectations with the incumbent of the role&lt;/li&gt;
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                    &lt;h5 class=&quot;card-subtitle list-group-item text-muted border-top border-bottom-0&quot;&gt;Work Around&lt;/h5&gt;
                    &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Slow down and ask for more time, where possible. &lt;/li&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Jot down what’s similar and what’s different in your experience and your ‘anchor’. Be conscious of these when taking decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                &lt;/ul&gt;    
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col mb-2&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;card text-center&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/availability_heuristic-post.jpg&quot; class=&quot;card-img-top&quot; alt=&quot;Monkey climbing a tree&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;small class=&quot;m-0 p-0 pb-2&quot;&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@zachspears?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Zachary Spears&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@pranesh_n/likes?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;card-body&quot;&gt;
                &lt;h4 class=&quot;card-title&quot;&gt;Availability Heuristic&lt;/h4&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;card-text&quot;&gt;Taking decisions based on the first information that comes to mind because we believe that it must be significant, hence we remembered it.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                    &lt;h5 class=&quot;card-subtitle list-group-item border-top border-bottom-0 text-muted&quot;&gt;Manifestations at work&lt;/h5&gt;
                    &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;“Remember the person from Chennai who couldn’t adjust to Delhi weather. Let’s look at regional candidates only please.”&lt;/li&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Selectively bringing information into a performance feedback session.&lt;/li&gt;
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                    &lt;h5 class=&quot;card-subtitle list-group-item text-muted border-top border-bottom-0&quot;&gt;Work Around&lt;/h5&gt;
                    &lt;ul class=&quot;list-group list-group-flush&quot;&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Blind the resumes. Mask information that may cause biases to creep in at a screening stage.&lt;/li&gt;
                        &lt;li class=&quot;list-group-item border-0&quot;&gt;Institute an ongoing process of feedback or at least document evidence (like a performance journal).&lt;/li&gt;
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                &lt;/ul&gt;    
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;form action=&quot;https://formspree.io/f/xjvpqqbe&quot; method=&quot;POST&quot; class=&quot;card&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;card-header&quot;&gt;If you liked our article, we also have a visual deck to share with your colleagues, peers and other contacts to help them recognise their own biases and those others around them may be exhibiting. Drop your details here and we’ll email it to you!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;card-body&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;form-group&quot;&gt;
        &lt;label for=&quot;inputEmail&quot;&gt;Email address&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;email&quot; name=&quot;email&quot; class=&quot;form-control&quot; id=&quot;inputEmail&quot; aria-describedby=&quot;emailHelp&quot; required=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;small id=&quot;emailHelp&quot; class=&quot;form-text text-muted&quot;&gt;We'll never share your email with anyone else.&lt;/small&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;form-group&quot;&gt;
        &lt;label for=&quot;fullName&quot;&gt;Full Name&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;text&quot; class=&quot;form-control&quot; id=&quot;fullName&quot; name=&quot;fullName&quot; required=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;Samriddhi Consulting is committed to protecting and respecting your privacy, and we’ll only use your personal information to administer your account and to provide the products and services you requested from us. From time to time, we would like to contact you about our products and services, as well as other content that may be of interest to you. If you consent to us contacting you for this purpose, please tick below to say how you would like us to contact you:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;In order to provide you the content requested, we need to store and process your personal data. If you consent to us storing your personal data for this purpose, please tick the checkbox below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;form-group form-check&quot;&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;form-check-input&quot; id=&quot;emailConsent&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;label class=&quot;form-check-label&quot; for=&quot;emailConsent&quot; name=&quot;emailConsent&quot;&gt;Please send me the deck by email&lt;/label&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;card-footer&quot;&gt;
    &lt;button type=&quot;submit&quot; class=&quot;btn btn-primary&quot;&gt;Submit&lt;/button&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 10:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/cognitive_biases_primer</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/cognitive_biases_primer</guid>
        
        
        <category>Organisation_Development</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Making Virtual Performance Management count</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s that time of the year again. We are scheduling reviews, blocking one-on-ones with direct reports and managers, and going over our performance records (even photos of that virtual game show you hosted to showcase your team management skills!). Like every year, performance management time brings a certain whiff in the air – part excitement, part trepidation and definitely a lot of time pressure. 
But that was every year and 2020 has not been like ‘every’ year! 
Just like the other aspects of people management, performance appraisals are also impacted this year. With most of the workforce working remotely for a large part of the year and many targets getting impacted, companies are rethinking their performance metrics closely. Not only are organisations reconsidering the year-gone-by, they are also reviewing how new targets should be set up. 
One could see an opportunity in this adversity. Many organisations are evaluating a move from their traditional annual performance appraisal cycle to the continuous performance cycle or an OKR-based (Objective and Key Results) approach. This was something that so many of us were mulling over for years but never found the right nudge. 2020 seems to have given everyone the right reasons to shed the traditional performance approach and move in favour of more progressive ones. 
There’s no doubt that this year’s performance exercise will be unlike anyone in the past. While there are several differences, we have put together this go-to guide to help us tide over one unique aspect of this year’s exercise – remote appraisals! For many managers, this could be the first time that their employees are not face-to-face with them during the appraisal. This guide is to help them prepare better and ensure they make the best of the appraisal session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1---choose-an-appropriate-environment&quot;&gt;1.   Choose an appropriate environment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Distractions are a reality in the virtual meeting, and so are technological ‘glitches’. Being prepared for both is important. Don’t keep a meeting immediately before or after your one-on-one with a team member. Encourage the team member to do the same. Work out a time when both of you are most productive to avoid virtual fatigue. Also align times with other people at home – perhaps a time when your internet bandwidth will be used least! 
The review should definitely be a video-based session otherwise it will slip into a monologue of one person talking, and the other listening with their audio and video switched off! 
And just like you would keep your review documents ready in a physical feedback session, keep everything handy for screen share in this case. If your organisation’s people practices allow, it might even be a good idea to share the doc ahead of the meeting, so your team members can go through it with less anxiety and jot down their thoughts or doubts. This way you can focus the meeting on actionable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2---be-realistic&quot;&gt;2.   Be realistic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2020 was tough for everyone – some more than others. Have you taken a good assessment of how targets changed during the year for your team members? If you had already called this out sometime during the year, great! If not, this may be a good time to have a detailed discussion around what comprises of realistic goals. Use these one-on-one’s to read the pulse on your team members better and build confidence that their performance is being fairly evaluated in the light of the changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, look at the team members who have gone over and above their work. Did they adapt their styles to meet the goals? Did they take extra initiative in another area? Did they do something that was not there on their original KRA sheet? Discuss with your HR beforehand, what your approach is to handle these outliers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-coach-more-listen-more&quot;&gt;3.	Coach more, listen more&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A classic performance feedback session is a discussion where the managers and employee speak about KRAs one by one, listen to manager feedback and close with ratings. This year calls for more. More listening. More understanding. More empathy. Your team members have gone through a lot to achieve what they have. Give them the platform to share their stories – struggle or valour as it may be! 
Appreciative Inquiry (AI) is a great tool to coach your team members in this situation, instead of just giving a direct feedback. AI is a strengths-based model that seeks to engage your audience in self-determined change. Because it focuses on the positive and encourages change from within, the results are far more sustaining that any other feedback model and that’s the reason we at Samriddhi also love using this tool a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-think-out-of-the-box&quot;&gt;4.	Think out of the box&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use your creativity this performance appraisal. Think of new metrics that may be more relevant in a virtual work setup, for e.g. response time could be an easy metric to find. Review notes from your slack or teams’ channels or zoom recordings. This could also be the time to really start implementing a competency framework if you don’t already. It takes all subjectivity out of the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now more than ever, a performance appraisal must be evidence-based and competency-focused. As we continue to be less visible, any rating of performance must be well-thought through and backed-up with examples of behaviors. Consider making 2021 goals short, objective and adaptive. Also, consider increasing the frequency of your performance discussions.
Here’s wishing everyone a highly productive appraisal season in this new normal!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;form action=&quot;https://formspree.io/f/meqpwzra&quot; method=&quot;POST&quot; class=&quot;card&quot;&gt;
  
  &lt;p class=&quot;card-header&quot;&gt;
    If you liked our article, we also have a visual deck to share with your managers as part of your organisation preparedness for this appraisal season. Drop your details here and we’ll email it to you!
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/performance_management_deck_form_image.jpg&quot; class=&quot;card-img-top&quot; alt=&quot;An image of a succulent plant&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;card-body&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;form-group&quot;&gt;
        &lt;label for=&quot;inputEmail&quot;&gt;Email address&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;email&quot; name=&quot;email&quot; class=&quot;form-control&quot; id=&quot;inputEmail&quot; aria-describedby=&quot;emailHelp&quot; required=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;small id=&quot;emailHelp&quot; class=&quot;form-text text-muted&quot;&gt;We'll never share your email with anyone else.&lt;/small&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;form-group&quot;&gt;
        &lt;label for=&quot;fullName&quot;&gt;Full Name&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;text&quot; class=&quot;form-control&quot; id=&quot;fullName&quot; name=&quot;fullName&quot; required=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;Samriddhi Consulting is committed to protecting and respecting your privacy, and we’ll only use your personal information to administer your account and to provide the products and services you requested from us. From time to time, we would like to contact you about our products and services, as well as other content that may be of interest to you. If you consent to us contacting you for this purpose, please tick below to say how you would like us to contact you:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;In order to provide you the content requested, we need to store and process your personal data. If you consent to us storing your personal data for this purpose, please tick the checkbox below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;form-group form-check&quot;&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;form-check-input&quot; id=&quot;emailConsent&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;label class=&quot;form-check-label&quot; for=&quot;emailConsent&quot; name=&quot;emailConsent&quot;&gt;Please send me the deck by email&lt;/label&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;card-footer&quot;&gt;
    &lt;button type=&quot;submit&quot; class=&quot;btn btn-primary&quot;&gt;Submit&lt;/button&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2021 10:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/making_virtual_performance_management_count</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/making_virtual_performance_management_count</guid>
        
        
        <category>Organisation_Development</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Celebrating work and diversity</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is exactly why I’m a fan of virtual facilitations! It brings people from different corners of the world together. Perhaps more importantly, it helps me filter the truly keen learners from those who have been mandated!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our certified diversity facilitator workshop on March 2nd was another testimony to my belief. All of us were there in that frame because we truly believed in the cause of inclusion. The discussions in the breakout rooms were evidence of how engaged a virtual setup can get because as a participant I am getting views from such a diverse audience about D&amp;amp;I. We all stayed till the end because we really wanted to reflect on what insights Shruthi Gokuldas - our fireside chat guest - had to bring in. Rarely do you come across a leader who is willing to use her stories and vulnerabilities to drive home important learnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design of the format further lent itself to deeper engagement. By sharing the pre-read on Cognitive Bias in advance, we had already primed the minds of our participants towards the session content. Such a format is powerful because it puts control into the learners’ hands. It required us to reach out to our participants in advance, through multiple channels but it was well worth it. They have the choice to read the content when they are in the best state to absorb that learning, leaving their minds free to absorb more during the actual session. The neuroscience of learning teaches us a thing or two about transferring pre-reads from our short-term memory to long-term memory! Critical content (in this case, the primer on Cognitive Bias because it forms the foundation of understanding diversity) should not only be shared in advance but also allowed to sit in the learners’ minds for at least one sleep cycle, thereafter reinforcing it (in our case, with a quickfire quiz!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got really ambitious in our breakout room activity and I want to thank every single one of our participants for engaging so deeply with the intense content. Breakouts lend themselves to open and candid discussions, diverse thoughts and clearer convergence because they allow people to work in small comfortable groups, where everyone has a voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there’s technology of course which I love! Virtual collaboration boards have replaced coloured post-it notes so efficiently. I never anyway liked the struggle of keeping the post-its stuck to the whiteboard whilst you debrief your activity! Besides, use the right tools, and you can keep the responses anonymous thereby creating a safe, open space for everyone to come forward and share ideas if you so plan in your activity. This is especially important for a topic like diversity and inclusion, where we struggle with our deep-rooted unconscious biases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our certified diversity facilitator workshop has been a journey well begun… A journey that has brought together people who believe in a strong cause of inclusion and making a difference through diversity. This is exactly the reason why we brought on-board Sumana Dutta from the Akshadhaa Foundation as our inclusion partner. Her tireless efforts on ensuring how people of different abilities can be integrated into the mainstream of organisations are critical to our context today and resonate deeply with us at Samriddhi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For us, diversity is not a once in a year reminder on a special day. It is not an elitist cause to support. It is a belief, a future that we believe is sustainable because it makes business sense. And I am today proud to have taken a small step to create this community.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2021 10:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/celebrating_work_and_diversity</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/celebrating_work_and_diversity</guid>
        
        
        <category>Instructional_Design</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Adapting GTM practice to the New Normal</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When the pandemic struck, it was evident that it would cause a tectonic change in the Go-to-Market (GTM) world. With so much turbulence, we decided to focus our GTM efforts in managing our Instructional Design practice, to weather the storm. As the skies cleared, it became immediately apparent that we had to zoom into our GTM practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have officially and audaciously split our GTM work into three key areas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;communitymanagement,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;funnelmanagement, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;userexperience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;community-management&quot;&gt;Community Management&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting with my experience around the Maggi crisis, I saw first-hand, a failure of the broadcast approach to marketing and the emergence of a concept where a brand was being defined by multiple stakeholders. While at some level this has always been true, brand owners were more in control in the past. This has been driven by increased mobile penetration and rapid advancements in user interface design that have made it significantly easier to enrol new users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having said that, the changes became far more explosive due to the pandemic. With forced lockdowns and fears of the unknown, people clamoured for the comfort of others and found it in the digital world. Physical distances no longer mattered and interest-based communities bloomed; ones that might not have survived in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, as early as Jun 2020 before the full impact of the crisis, nearly 40% of online communities indicated that their growth had accelerated, 25% of those indicating a massive increase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see this as a key change for how brands are built – by the community, for the community and in many cases, by the community. Massive democratization of the entire brand value creation process is in play and we seek to build capacity to align ourselves, our customers and the broader community to these changes. Which brings me to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;funnel-management&quot;&gt;Funnel Management&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In close alignment with democratization of brands, there is a need for organizations to redefine what was earlier known as the #ordertocash cycle. While tools existed in the past to get into granular metrics of the sales funnel, they lacked the scale to provide meaningful and statistically significant results for many organizations. As consumers were forced to adopt more digital means to order and pay for their everyday needs, digital tools got the scale they hitherto lacked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost of measuring leads and lags has come down significantly and measurement quality has increased dramatically. These metrics are now available real-time and are more definitive indicators of behaviour over intent-based data. For the &lt;a href=&quot;https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/usher_in_the_era_of_agility&quot;&gt;agile&lt;/a&gt; organisation, this can unlock tremendous value and we hope to be a part of that journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;user-experience&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://samriddhiconsulting.com/user_experience/home&quot;&gt;User Experience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digitalisation has colossally impacted everyone in the value creation cycle – sales, marketing, operations, IT, supply chain, finance, human resources – all parts of a business. While we think of this very often from a customer interface point of view, it is cold reality that employees ought to make significant changes in the way they deliver value to customers. This becomes dramatically complicated when we think of the changes that may be required to make workplaces more accessible and intuitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should organizations create interfaces similar to actual physical experiences or should they make them unique to stay distinct? Should interfaces be simple and easy to navigate or should they replace humans who would essay a certain role? There are many such questions but no easy answers. We seek to partner and learn with organisations who want to solve these puzzles and make the workplace future-ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since you’ve read till here, we have a small favour to ask you. While we are investing strengthen our capabilities, we know we cannot do it alone. Please help us to connect with other professionals and organisations in your network who have built solutions for these spaces. We’re excited by what these synergies could bring for our clients and indeed to the entire ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, we are seeking to engage with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UX Design specialists with an eye for minimalistic designs. While we are open to other approaches, we currently believe this is best expressed vide figma&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Front-End Development experts who are performance-oriented (technicalseo) developers, understand how Google Search works and can integrate complex solutions into light interfaces. We use a lot of Chrome Web-Tools including Lighthouse and Rich-Results.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2021 10:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/general/changes_in_gtm_practice</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samriddhiconsulting.com/general/changes_in_gtm_practice</guid>
        
        
        <category>General</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Usher in the era of Agility</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;At the outset, a very happy New year to everyone. Never has it felt like such an achievement! The last year felt like a Ninja obstacle course, what with the ongoing pandemic, series of lockdowns and varied protests across the world. No doubt, we have all emerged better, stronger and more grateful on the other side but it’s now time to look ahead at what this new year could bring for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2020 has prepared us in a journey towards agility. Our response time and resilience in the face of crisis was tested in so many different ways last year. Almost every business had to think differently. In some situations, it was just important to turn up and engage with employees and customers. Even if the response was not optimised, our last-minute agility demanded that we reacted and adapted. Many of us felt the repercussions spill into our personal lives and interpersonal relationships too. 
Every day of the year, we were adapting to the situation, to the present. But now it’s about adapting to the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter what the soothsayers say about 2021, there’s one thing we will all agree upon. This year will belong to the agile. To those who stay strong yet flexible. Those who demonstrate speed in evaluating the circumstances. To those who act with courage but care. To those of us who stay focused on the goal, rather than how we get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Oxford English Dictionary defines Agility as the “ability to move quickly and easily”, being agile is about having a growth mindset. &lt;a href=&quot;https://assets.thoughtworks.com/articles/adaptive-leadership-accelerating-enterprise-agility-jim-highsmith-thoughtworks.pdf&quot;&gt;James Highsmith puts it best&lt;/a&gt; that being agile includes the ability to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engage&lt;/strong&gt; by collaborating, communicating and inspiring&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explore&lt;/strong&gt; by becoming a great lifelong learner&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resolve Issues&lt;/strong&gt; while navigating ambiguity and paradox&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adapt&lt;/strong&gt; by being open to change and embracing the change process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agility cannot be built in the absence of information – particularly about the changes in the environment and hence engaging with the situation is a key first step. Decentralised systems and processes allow for faster and greater exploration. Breaking down silos and creating opportunities for frequent ideas sharing and knowledge transfer goes a long way in resolving issues and increasing agility. This helps in building an adaptive leader or a culture that quickly blends in the changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, unless agility is part of the organisation’s deep-rooted culture, it will only take the next crisis to throw the ship off. Since 2000, ‘agile’ has increasingly been used as a management practice in project management and technology implementations. However few organisations took actionable measures to build an agile culture, develop agile leaders within and respond to their customers and changing markets with agility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2021 is the time to really build our muscle and put agility into action, in all aspects of our lives – personal and professional&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 10:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/usher_in_the_era_of_agility</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/usher_in_the_era_of_agility</guid>
        
        
        <category>Instructional_Design</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Universal Design for Learning - An Introduction</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The human mind in general and how it learns, in specific, has been a realm of fascination and delight for me, for many years now. We used to think that the whole subject of learning new things ends once we finish our formal education and enter the workplace. Of course, now we know that the truth couldn’t be further from there. Learning for life is a deeper reality than earlier considered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either way, whether approaching formal academic education or professional learning, the truth about how our mind absorbs new information remains the same. More importantly, the challenges around those learning are also similar - the primary one amongst them being how to make learning accessible to everyone. When I think about the building blocks of learning, I start with accessibility. How will a person learn if the knowledge or skill being learnt is difficult to access?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img srcset=&quot;/assets/images/udlg_graphic_organiser_v2-2-post550.jpg 550w, /assets/images/udlg_graphic_organiser_v2-2-post750.jpg 750w /assets/images/udlg_graphic_organiser_v2-2-post.jpg 1200w&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/udlg_graphic_organiser_v2-2-post.jpg&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width:650px) 550w, 750w, 1200w&quot; class=&quot;img-fluid float-left&quot; alt=&quot;A child building a rocket ship with blocks&quot; style=&quot;max-height: 70vh; width: auto;&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does accessibility mean in the context of learning design? This is one of the first questions I ask as an instructional designer. For me, the Universal Design for Learning or UDL has always provided a comprehensive yet simple framework to help answer this question. In this three-
part series on UDL, I hope to share some of the key features of UDL and how it has helped me in my journey as an instructional designer over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accessibility as per UDL refers to an inclusive learning design that ensures that different types of learners engage with the content in multiple ways and find the motivation to apply it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UDL encompasses a range of principles to ensure that learning content motivates all types of learners, the content is represented in a variety of ways and the learner engagement is approached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my study as an instructional designer, when I first came across UDL, I was simply fascinated by the completeness of this structure. At first glance, it looked like an off-shoot of Kolb’s work on the different learning styles to me. However, it just took a scratch of reading to understand that learning styles are focused on ‘fixing the learner’ but UDL is focused on fixing the learning experience on the whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is what makes this body of work so intense and I’ve never stopped going back to it as my sine qua non. It takes a lot of research and deep analysis of learning and neuroscience to develop a model like UDL. It’s deceptively simple and is mostly used for academic learning design to ensure our classrooms are more inclusive to all types of learners. The possibilities of applying it into our professional learning experiences are however endless.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 10:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/universal_design_for_learning-an_introduction</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/universal_design_for_learning-an_introduction</guid>
        
        
        <category>Instructional_Design</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
