<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>All things Growth | Samriddhi Consulting</title>
    <description>At Samriddhi, we love to look forward and walk into uncharted territories to bring back innovative solutions for our partner clients</description>
    <link>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 17:01:45 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 17:01:45 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.1.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Unconscious biases and the conundrums of parenting</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your children are not your children.&lt;/p&gt;
     &lt;p&gt;They are the sons and daughters of Life’s longing for itself&lt;/p&gt;
     &lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;-	Kahlil Gibran&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are so many dimensions to a parent-child relationship, the events of the past few months have made me notice the times we – as parents – encourage unconscious biases amongst our children, even in the most innocent of conversations. I often wonder if parenting in the current times is harder or easier than a few generations ago. It felt easy because growing up, our parents would simply “tell” us what to do and we’d listen. They were after all the ultimate authority figures in our life, perhaps after our teachers. However, as we have grown, and realised that sometimes in our quest to continue finding authority figures in our lives – in managers, partners or even friends, we end up in toxic relationships, and with tons of biases!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exercising ‘authority’ over our children is a very delicate balance to be maintained. A lot of us overcome it over the years, but it always leaves unconscious biases deep within. Parents try to protect their children and give a decision-making framework to work within. Don’t talk to someone dressed up like that or be careful if you’re going to a neighbourhood dominated by a particular group. However, involving children in the ‘process’ of decision making is more important than involving them in the outcome. The outcome is for them to see and in most cases execute, but the process remains hidden, and that’s where a large number of dilemmas are handled, habits are formed and references created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a parent now, I don’t know how to help my ten-year-old come to understand himself better, and be independent - physically, mentally, emotionally, spiritually. But I do know that ‘telling what to think’ is something I will stay away from. It’s a huge ask and it will conflict with my values sometimes. For example, a few days ago while watching a Netflix series, my son had a plethora of questions and opinions about homosexuals. Or when he reads about basic rights at school and asks about our domestic helps. I’ve been raised to ‘not think’ about these issues. To accept certain societal norms as facts but if I continue that tradition, I’m encouraging the legacy of biases and giving my son a limited mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My parents are great people, educated and well meaning. They gave us exposure and freedom, but they probably didn’t have the courage to rise over their personal circumstances and think about giving us principles that last the test of time and place. Principles that could be applied everywhere and would still hold true. Like cardinal truths, these are guiding lights. Because parents aren’t around all the time, their job is only to equip their children with guiding principles and a checklist that helps them take quick effective decisions in a variety of situations. The decisions may not be perfect, but it’ll help them get past whatever they are facing - bullying, relationships, careers, biases and so many others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that doesn’t change whether I am an 18th century parent or raising a millennial. If I possess the courage and vulnerability to teach my child – not what to think and what opinions to form but how to think and how to discuss opinions, I have raised a human who can thrive in any era, in any culture. Then, when we get to corporate workplaces, we don’t have to be taught behaviours like “don’t judge” and “don’t be biased”. What a save from the unlearning and relearning to correct our frames of reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have tried to correct mine, but I still keep questioning them and re-calibrating them with what is happening around me. Feels like I’ve got a breakthrough – no matter how small, but remind me to keep doing a rain check every now and then!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation%20development/2020/09/13/unconscious_biases_and_the_conondrum_of_parenting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation%20development/2020/09/13/unconscious_biases_and_the_conondrum_of_parenting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Organisation Development</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bite-size your way to productivity</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There are some definite advantages to working from home and enough has been written about those since March 2020. Covid-19 however has added an unfortunate variable of ‘work at home’ to an endless quantum of work from home - thereby blurring boundaries and causing burnout. With schools and day cares schools, domestic help limited and restaurants closed, the entire conundrum of ‘how to be productive working at home’ suddenly fell upon us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of us are on the overworked end of the spectrum. We don’t know when to stop working, hopping from one task to another and one call to another, never getting a moment to rest. Some others though are on the overwhelmed end of the spectrum. Never knowing where to start from because between video calls, emails and presentations, they also have to squeeze in cooking, cleaning and parenting! Its daunting – especially for structure people like me, who created their next day’s to-do list before going to bed every night!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of my friends are fortunately in the middle of this work-life balance spectrum. Speaking to them was very insightful and helped me uncover the concept of bite-sizing tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a learning and development professional, I’m a huge fan of bite sized learning. So this was a natural progression for me. Breaking down something large and daunting into chewable chunks leads to greater effectiveness. And it appears that it’s as true for learning as it is for productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept is simple - if a task takes me one hour to complete, and I am unable to schedule a clear one hour in my day, due to interruptions at home, then I need to chunk it down. If I can squeeze in 15 minutes, I start the task. If I manage 20 minutes, that’s great. Or else I leave it at 15, and come back when I get my next 15 minutes window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I know this may sound over simplistic, but once you practice it, you’ll be surprised at how powerful it is in breaking you out of a procrastination loop. Plus, for me personally this technique works wonders because most of my work involves thinking and chewing on those thoughts. The actual time I need to spend in front of a laptop is very less if my thoughts are well structured and deeply thought through. So you could find me deep me thought, folding laundry, or some other such mundane task!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only does the bite-sizing technique help you fit in so much more during the day, the breaks actually help cut the monotony and give your body the much needed physical movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the next time your partner asks you to do the dishes, schedule it between your presentations and email marathons, and you may surprise yourself with the results!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation%20development/2020/08/17/Bite-size_your_way_to_productivity.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation%20development/2020/08/17/Bite-size_your_way_to_productivity.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Organisation Development</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>SEO| UX - 7 Essentials - A Review</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The search-phrase “SEO Essentials” yields a number of results; most people agree on a number of common items, and there are points of disagreement too. I came across an &lt;a href=&quot;https://dev.to/lampewebdev/top-7-essential-seo-optimizations-for-you-to-learn-in-2019-15i5&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; on the subject recently. The author makes some good observations and I quote him :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-alt-attribute-in-img-tags&quot;&gt;The &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;alt&lt;/code&gt; attribute in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;img&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tags&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br class=&quot;my-4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Images form a large part of modern web design and so this one is rather straightforward and highly recommended by multiple SEO practitioners. The author shares examples and I quote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br class=&quot;my-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Some bad examples
      &lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;img src=&quot;/dog.png&quot;&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;img src=&quot;/dog.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;img src=&quot;/dog.png&quot; alt=&quot;dog&quot;&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;img src=&quot;/dog.png&quot; alt=&quot;animal dog ball red&quot;&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Some good examples
      &lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;img src=&quot;/dog.png&quot; alt=&quot;A dog that play with a red ball&quot;&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;img src=&quot;/billGates.png&quot; alt=&quot;Bill Gates, former CEO of Microsoft&quot;&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;img src=&quot;/123-img.png&quot; alt=&quot;Two girls playing on an playground&quot;&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br class=&quot;my-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key is to think of the screen-reader users who cant see the image, so describing it as much as possible. Its not easy, when you’re coding, your mind is focused often on algorithm and code. I would recommend making the alt tag review a part of your release process, this way you make sure the checkbox gets ticked and at a time when you’re thinking less about the code and more about the user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this is seems simple, it definitely requires rigour and worth its weight in SEO gold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br class=&quot;my-4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;title-structure&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; structure&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a no-brainer. &lt;strong&gt;Titles are critical.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author, rather usefully, recommends a length of 60 chars for the title and using the format:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;title&amp;gt;
        Primary Keyword - Secondary Keyword | Brand Name
    &amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br class=&quot;my-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a slightly different opinion about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Without doubt, titles are critical.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For discovery, the search engine results are critical, but thereafter, its all about winning on the bookmarks bar, on browser tabs, etc. Hence, IMHO, the first 8 characters are critical. The next part should flow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am guilty of preaching without practicing this, and yet awareness is the first step :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br class=&quot;my-4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;html-langvarlanguage-check-the-language-tag-in-your-boilerplates&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;html lang=&quot;varLanguage&quot;&lt;/code&gt; check the language tag in your boilerplates&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be tricky. While we all know that using the right language is critical, and as the author points out, many boilerplates, templates and frameworks tend to default to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;html lang=&quot;en&quot;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br class=&quot;my-4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;use-relnofollow-on-links-shared-by-users&quot;&gt;Use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&lt;/code&gt; on links shared by users&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Important, of course, but might not find a place in an SEO essentials list. Sample quote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;a href=&quot;http://www.unknown.com/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&amp;gt;Paid or not trusted content&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br class=&quot;my-4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;use-relcanonical-if-you-have-multiple-pages-with-the-same-content&quot;&gt;Use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rel=&quot;canonical&quot;&lt;/code&gt; if you have multiple pages with the same content&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have one of those old websites that has a mobile page, an AMP page and a regular desktop page all of which have the same content, then this is important. Again, not an essential item on my list because who makes Non-Responsive websites anymore?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br class=&quot;my-4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;use-meta-nameviewport&quot;&gt;Use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;meta name=&quot;viewport&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the author rightly points out, not something which directly impacts SEO. Having said that, this would be on my &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; essentials list&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br class=&quot;my-4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;use-media-queries&quot;&gt;Use media queries&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think this is an SEO essentials item, but no doubt an absolutely essential item to consider. I am a fan of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://getbootstrap.com/&quot;&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; framework. However, not an item on my SEO Essentials list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/user%20experience/2020/06/02/SEO_UX_7_Essentials.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samriddhiconsulting.com/user%20experience/2020/06/02/SEO_UX_7_Essentials.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>User Experience</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>To New Beginnings</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Having entered a new decade, I can’t help but look back at the decade gone by and wonder if there’s ever been such a game-changing ten-year run for HR professionals – what with HR automation, people analytics, gig economy, millennials and learning-on-the-go challenging every paradigm of people management for the better. HR is moving from processing paper to making individuals feel valued in the organisation and supporting their talent journeys&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Difficult to see. Always in motion is the future&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;-Yoda (Episode V: The Empire Strikes Back)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are exciting times to be working on people capability. Not only are the employees more aware about the possibilities and opportunities that exist to enable them, their managers are more receptive than ever. This has largely to do with the fact that learning or talent development has become more embedded into the employee’s role, rather than a stand-alone training program with little transferability into the learner’s job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is all the more exciting about building people capability in these times is the ecosystem we are working in – the community that wants to learn and become better than yesterday. Our peers who share knowledge and new learning as freely as they share their Instagram updates. The manager who spend their after-work hours learning a new tech-tool from a college grad. The HR management systems that are making way for Employee Experience Platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industrial Revolution 4.0 has indeed come knocking at our doors in style! I can’t wait to see how this unfolds in the 2020s and the endless possibilities it brings for us to leverage.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional%20design/2020/06/01/to_new_beginnings.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional%20design/2020/06/01/to_new_beginnings.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Instructional Design</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Of cultures and new hires</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot of talk about culture fit, when it comes to hiring for our teams. I’ve heard many managers using the phrase rather loosely when they can’t put a finger on the pulse. Now if you’ve ever tried asking these recruiting managers - what exactly is a culture fit for them – chances are they can’t always describe it to you in objective terms. It is indeed a tough ask because often it is a soft, fuzzy feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can culture fitment really be quantified then? Psychometric assessments and value-based tests have made us come closer to an answer. However, the moment of truth usually takes place in the interview – when the recruiting manager and the candidate are sitting face to face from each other. That fuzzy feeling is to be trusted, no matter what the psychometrics may say. The question is only if we can find a common language to describe it to other stakeholders, and possibly even the candidate (in an ideal world!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always felt that the key to finding the right words to express is often to step back and first check if it all adds up inside our heads. In this case too, before we try to find a common language, the first step is to break down the interview experience in our heads and write down the way you felt meeting the candidate. Did the person come across as genuine or was s/he putting too much effort into the process? Did the person think through enough before answering? Did his/her answers were consistent with everything else you’ve seen about the candidate in the interview process? Write down some of these pointers to look out for before the interview. You can lean on your earlier experience or even speak to some experienced interviewers in your company for inspiration. It helps to know what else you’re looking for, apart from the functional skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just taking our filters off and knowing how the interview felt for you is extremely useful to write down these ‘descriptors’. Once you have a list of these words, the next step is to sit with your HR or an experienced recruiter in your organisation who can help you bucket these words into your company’s culture framework. This is why many companies follow a best practice of having a two-member panel for every interview. It gives the interviewers someone to bounce off their thoughts, feelings and descriptors with, within the frame of the company’s culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say, accountability is something your organisation values in a new hire. You pick on all the large and small signs that add up to accountable behaviour. Did the person arrive in time, maybe called up in advance and checked for directions and parking arrangements? These small details not just show the interest one takes in the role, but also ownership. I’ve often experienced candidates who start talking about the company they are interviewing with, as ‘us’ – turn out to be very high on accountability when hired. Something else may work for you as an interviewer, and a hiring manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing in a new hire into your team is a major decision and taking into account all parameters – functional and otherwise – is a wise step. When you know what you’re looking for, you can even figure out in the interview if your near-perfect candidate can pick up on a small cultural nuance or not. That’s something that will be hard to interpret just by looking at a psychometric report or a test, and it could just be the difference between a good hire and a not-so-good one.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation%20development/2020/05/30/of_cultures_and_new_hires.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation%20development/2020/05/30/of_cultures_and_new_hires.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Organisation Development</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>An introduction to Design Thinking</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I came across an article on Design Thinking recently. Now Design Thinking isn’t a new catchword. It has been around for a while now, with various industries – from manufacturing to consulting and even interestingly, instructional designers – trying to incorporate the principles of design thinking into their work. The reasons can be manifold – some are trying to make their product or service more relevant to the customer, others are making the process more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are living in a connected world where customers are seeking for the best, equipped with more information that has been collected from more sources than ever before. Customers today are becoming increasingly sophisticated and impatient. Adding to this is the prevalence of social networks and the internet that has led on to an increased customer-to-customer interaction. Hence the customers not just know what they want, they know how and where to get it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To cater to this increased expectations of quality, reliability, safety, utility and survive the hyper-competitive business environment, the manufacturers and service providers are determined to ensure a steady stream of product and technology options that is developed on the basis of the company’s sense of where the market is headed. A large part of it is driven by the customers as the ‘social currency’ is changing the face of the product or service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My limited reading on the subject has led me to understand a little about design thinking and be intrigued by it. Design Thinking means keeping the customer in mind all the time while driving innovations which are technologically feasible and economically viable. Manufacturers around the world have drawn their attention to Design Thinking as a concept of innovation management as the organizations have opened their minds to learn from designers in being creative and innovative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Design Thinker sets the customer at the heart of thinking, is collaborative by integrating different point of views, and focuses on the future instead of considering how things work today. A design process model includes five vital steps: empathise with the customer, the analysis of the problem, designing the solution, the implementation, and the evaluation of the solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is imperative to start, by deeply understanding the customer, defining solution success in customer words and then continuously looking to improve. Leaders need to drive the change by maintaining a customer-focused mindset in every communication and decision made. Leading organizations today are using open and collaborative approach to innovation. The collaboration here is not just within the design thinking team members but also with the customers - to deepen the customer understanding and increase the odds of success of the solution. An amalgamation of diverse perspectives can create something beautiful and altogether new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would say that design thinking is as much about mind shift as it is about innovation, and even though implementation might take a couple of years to find its ground, the solutions brought about by design thinking shall prove to strengthen relevance, application and most importantly sustainability in the coming days. I’d love to hear your thoughts, opinions and experiments with Design Thinking!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/user%20experience/2020/05/29/design_thinking.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samriddhiconsulting.com/user%20experience/2020/05/29/design_thinking.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>User Experience</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Workforce Mash-up!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;While the Traditional are close to retiring, the other four are still very active in the workplace dynamics. Managing these often-conflicting views and needs of a diverse workforce that may cover a wide range of generations – from the Baby Boomers and Gen X to millennials and Gen Z – is a challenge for many organisations. The tension is visible between the highly experienced Baby Boomers who are mostly at the helm in their roles, the disaffected Gen Xer and the technologically savvy millennials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The foundation of these differences lie in the widely different values held by each generation. Baby boomers, having grown up in a post-independence era of constrained resources and opportunities, strongly believe in the values of hard work and organisational loyalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gen Xers, on the other hand, are highly extrinsically motivated. During their working years, they have paid off their education loans and home loans, while saving for their children’s education and their own retirement. No doubt then, they work hard – sometimes very hard – for an overtime, a promotion or a job change promising better prospects, and take nothing for granted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As if the conflicts between these two weren’t enough, a huge number of millennials or Gen Y has entered the work place. It is estimated that by 2020, 50% of the global workforce will comprise of millennials. As per surveys, most millennials are happy working alongside other generations and they value older mentors – indeed, they have been raised in an era where the internet brought the world closer and live news feeds and Facebook ensured wide spread collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are underlying signs of tensions. As per a study by PwC (Millennials at Work, 2011) 38% millennials say that older senior management do not relate to younger workers, and 34% say that their personal drive was intimidating to other generations. And almost half felt that their managers did not always understand the way they use technology at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is some research to suggest that this may be true. The older generations sense entitlement in the millennials. It is not unusual to hear a millennial being described as “smart but lacking motivation”, but this could just as well have meant “smart but I don’t understand his/her motivation”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The millennial is not your average 9 – 5 worker. They are interested in business beyond their realm of work. They will ask questions about the company’s vision, mission and purpose. They aspire to work for organisations which make a larger difference to the community. The culture and values the organisation stands for and the learning opportunities it offers them are key infliction points. Well networked, millennials rely less on the organisation for these inputs and more on social media and word of mouth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once on-board too, Gen Y is posing an exciting opportunity – for the first time the workplaces are getting intrinsically motivated people, and this is where the key talent differentiator rests. Organisations that will leverage this intrinsic motivation will emerge winners in the long run. Whoever said this will be easy is certainly joking! Baby Boomers and Gen Xers will have to unlearn and relearn the dynamics of people management. They need to re-design work plans and use their imagination to “measure performance”. Structures and hierarchies stifle the drive of most Millennials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other challenges in bridging this inter-generational gap is to create growth paths such that the Gen Y doesn’t feel blocked. With fitness levels increasing, the Gen X is looking to retire much later. This will create blocks in the traditional corporate ladder, but if HR opens a plethora of learning and growth opportunities for them – in the shape of lateral movements, secondments, rotations and strategic projects – the millennials will find their calling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HR also has to be prepared to face another demographic challenge - millennials will find themselves managing older workers, some of whom may be resentful of the same. Managing a multi-generational work force demands strong leadership, recognition through the organisation that different generations may need different styles of management and a transparent performance management system that is progressive and transparent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting future ready is the only way ahead. With Gen Z getting ready to jump into the work places sooner than any of their previous generations, are organisations ready to handle this flurry? Born just as the millennium changed, the Gen Z is the first truly digital cluster of workers. They can’t be painted with the millennials brush – multi taskers, easily distracted and entrepreneurial, this bunch of workers will not wait to complete their education to enter the workplace. Therefore, e-learning and sabbaticals have to become in-built into their career plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A progressive HR will replace traditional hierarchies with seamless work structures to effectively manage this melting pot of generations. ‘One size fits all’ programs will no longer be valued and technology plays a pivotal role in this arena. Learning management systems (LMS) to map individual e-learning needs, leveraging digital media to attract and retain the right young talent, and using advanced people management software to track their progression, are just some of the areas where technology can lend an edge to organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of change needs to be created on the intangibles though. The multi-generational workplaces can either turn into war zones or can transform into collaborative, respected centres of excellence that are looked up to in organisations. The latter is possible by only focussing on the strengths of each generation. Mentoring programs are the best example here. Baby Boomers and Gen X come with a gold mine of tactical and strategic experience, which is missing in the distracted millennials or Gen Z. The latter on the other hand are the best teachers on using technology and enhancing workplace productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest priority for HR thus becomes building trust. It is easier said than done, but once it is revealed to each of the generations that their drives and ambitions are exclusive yet complimenting each other, their insecurities can turn into synergies. Extensive coaching to senior employees on handling the younger workers, as well as sensitisation of the millennials to adapt to the older generation is a way forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s in it for the organisation, you may still ask? A lot! Beyond large savings in attracting and retaining the right talent, the organisations are assured a happy, engaged workforce which is motivated for the right reasons apart from pay. Their employees believe in the vision and work towards improved productivity, which in turn leads to increased customer satisfaction and quality. And the best benefit perhaps is knowledge management. The hard work and expertise of the older generations is fused with the energy and productive efficiency of the younger, to create a truly future ready organisation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation%20development/2020/05/28/workplace_warfare.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation%20development/2020/05/28/workplace_warfare.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Organisation Development</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Neuroscience of Leadership</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s ten o’clock on a Monday morning. The conference room starts to fill up with swarms of employees – eager to hear the business re-structuring plans. Tension was palpable in the air and all eyes were on the door. Sachin walks into the room – a coffee mug in one hand and his presentation deck in the other. His relaxed stride and confident eye contact set the tone of the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost symbolically, he parks his presentation deck at the lectern and walks right through the centre – standing next to one of his employees. “There was a time, not too long ago, when I stood in this very room not as a CEO but a deputy sales manager,” he started. The journey had started as Sachin took his employees back in time, leading them slowly to the difficult times today and finally showing the possibilities of the future. In this journey though, their CEO became one of them and each employee travelled with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sachin is the new avatar of leaders who have evolved from slide decks and PowerPoints to connecting with their teams at an emotional level through story-telling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now know from neuroscience that our brains can make connections much faster when emotionally triggered. A neurochemical called oxytocin, an ‘empathy’ hormone that helps people bond is produced when we are trusted or shown a kindness. It motivates cooperation with others by building an ability to understand others’ emotions and reactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, what is more interesting is that we can try and hack the oxytocin system and motivate people to display empathetic or collaborative behaviour. Story-telling is one such hack that leaders have used for generations, and is now coming in the fore-front.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Storytelling has been with us as long as there have been people. From the ancient cave-man to Aristotle, from Martin Luther King to Mahatma Gandhi, story-telling has been the mainstay of leaders across all cultures and eras. By giving a vision that moves people, these leaders have been able to achieve unthinkable results. This is the power of story-telling for leadership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human brains are hard-wired to connect with stories. In a corporate context, while facts and figures are great, there’s nothing quite like a customer or employee story to captivate hearts and minds. That is because facts and figures activate two regions in the brain – Wernicke’s area which controls language comprehension and the Broca’s area which controls language processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But stories? They can activate upto 7 regions in the brain – each region is triggered by a particular sense in the story, for eg. while language triggers the Wernicke’s area and the Broca’s area, Sounds fires up the Auditory Cortex, Colors and Shapes activate the Visual Cortex, Movement trigger the Motor Cortex, etc.
Not only do stories spark off a larger part of the brain, they lead to emotional responses. Focusing on the thoughts and feelings of the protagonist of the story has a lasting effect on the ‘stickiness’ of the message. Our left brain builds narratives to make sense of our world and our actions. If the story is able to create that tension then it is likely that attentive viewers/listeners will come to share the emotions of the characters in it, and after it ends, likely to continue mimicking the feelings and behaviors of those characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our story above, when Sachin describes his journey from a deputy manager to CEO, the people he met, the products he sold, the places he travelled to - we don’t just have a mental image – we are virtually experiencing the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The usage of technology like Virtual Reality is under a lot of discussion today to bring the audience closer to the real scenario. If you think about it, storytelling is the foundation version of modern day VR since they allow us to experience other places, characters, events and consequences purely by stimulating our imaginations. Technology too relies on stories - a well-designed plot and characters one can connect to, are essential to audience engagement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psychologists refer to this use of stories, archetypes or models as narrative transport. It occurs when we are fully immersed in the story – it’s characters, the context and the emotions. When the brain engages with character-driven stories involving emotional content, they result in a better understanding of the key points a speaker wishes to make. Recall of these points and their impact is significantly larger because the audience is hooked to the outcome. It is studied that with greater empathy comes a deeper transportation experience.
So the next time you want to motivate, persuade, or be remembered, start with a story of human struggle and eventual triumph which will capture people’s hearts – by first attracting their brains. Why should customers or a person on the street care about the project you are proposing? How does it change the world or improve lives? How will people feel when it is complete? These are the components that make your information persuasive and memorable like Sachin’s story.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional%20design/2020/05/21/The_neuroscience_of_leadership.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional%20design/2020/05/21/The_neuroscience_of_leadership.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Instructional Design</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
