<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-04-17T15:27:12+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">All things Growth | Samriddhi Consulting</title><subtitle>At Samriddhi, we love to look forward and walk into uncharted territories to bring back innovative solutions for our partner clients</subtitle><author><name>vidhi</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Inter-generational Disruption at workplaces</title><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/inter-generational-disruption" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Inter-generational Disruption at workplaces" /><published>2022-04-12T10:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-04-12T10:30:00+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/inter-generational-disruption</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/inter-generational-disruption">&lt;p&gt;Managing the needs of a diverse workforce that may cover a wide range of generations is a challenge for any organisation. In this second blogpost, I’m taking a closer look at what questions this may pose to organisations and what solutions businesses can consider:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;text-center&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is Part 2 of the Generations Series. Read Part 1 &lt;a href=&quot;/organisation_development/inter-generational-diversity&quot;&gt;Inter-generational Diversity is getting real&lt;/a&gt; and Part 3 &lt;a href=&quot;/organisation_development/making-generational-diversity-work&quot;&gt;Making generational diversity work for you&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-how-does-my-business-vision-mission-and-values-inspire-all-generations&quot;&gt;1. How does my business vision, mission, and values inspire all generations?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key challenges that organisations and HR professionals face today is motivating these conflicting value systems. How does a business define its purpose or vision, which transcends across four generations, while at the same time resonates with each of them and keeps pace with the changing world on the outside to ensure relevance? For traditional businesses, sustenance or profitability was the key driver. With baby boomers and Gen X’ers at the helm, this purpose was aligned to the leaders’ values. Once millennials start to take up leadership roles, the business’ raison d’etre will need to expand. We are already seeing this with several new start-ups like &lt;a href=&quot;https://scafefabrics.com/en-global/about/particular&quot;&gt;S.café&lt;/a&gt; (Fabric created from recycled coffee beans) or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aircarbon.co/&quot;&gt;AirCarbon&lt;/a&gt; (a highly awarded carbon-negative product), which have sustainable growth at the core of their functioning. Their belief in working on meaningful projects, that will bring about resource optimisation is acute and widespread. In their pursuit of well-meaning goals like supporting the environment or reducing their carbon footprint, these businesses are conscious of the role of profitability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-how-do-i-measure-and-reward-success-or-performance-for-a-wide-range-of-generations&quot;&gt;2. How do I measure and reward success or performance for a wide range of generations?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the current context, it is not sufficient to just define meaningful goals and chart out a path to achieve them. How we measure success is changing drastically across different generations. While a Baby Boomer may still need to refer to long term targets and yearly reviews, it is important for the organisation to make room for other dashboards like OKRs to provide constant navigation to the Millennials and Gen Z. Rewarding and celebrating successes has always played an important part in an employee’s journey. The way these successes are rewarded has changed too and will continue to change as we go through the ‘turnings’ of generations. In an era of constrained opportunities or resources, monetary rewards added a lot of value, as did celebrating loyalty, for example in the form of long service awards. However, organisations are now introducing reward and recognition practices that help an employee connect with their passion or with the larger purpose of the organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-how-can-i-create-meaningful-career-paths-for-the-different-generations&quot;&gt;3. How can I create meaningful career paths for the different generations?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other challenges in bridging this inter-generational gap are to create growth paths such that Gen Y doesn’t feel blocked. With fitness levels increasing, Gen X is looking to retire much later. This will create blocks in the traditional corporate ladder, but with organisations opening a plethora of learning and growth opportunities for them – in the shape of lateral movements, secondments, rotations and strategic projects – the millennials are finding their calling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations also have to be prepared to face another demographic challenge. Millennials are increasingly finding themselves managing older workers, some of whom may be resentful of the same. Managing a multi-generational workforce demands strong leadership, recognition through the organisation that different generations may need different styles of management and a transparent people processes that is progressive and fair. This also calls for sensitisation of the different cohorts on how to work across generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-how-can-i-design-inclusive-communication-processes-and-messages&quot;&gt;4. How can I design inclusive communication processes and messages?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Managing a workforce that is increasingly diverse in age is not an easy task for employers. A 2017 study by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.roberthalf.com/blog/management-tips/where-managers-need-to-improve-most?utm_campaign=Press_Release&amp;amp;utm_medium=Link&amp;amp;utm_source=Press_Release&quot;&gt;Robert Half Management Resources&lt;/a&gt; found that communication is the most difficult aspect of workplace management, with up to four generations of employees. Specifically, 30% of executives surveyed said communication skills are the biggest difference between employees across generations. While almost all (90%) of respondents prefer to have colleagues of different ages and believe that a multi-generational workplace is mutually beneficial, according to a new international survey of workers aged 18-65, 81% of them agree that the main difference between generations in the workplace is communication styles. Additionally, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.randstad.com/workforce-insights/global-hr-research/randstad-workmonitor/&quot;&gt;Randstad Work Monitor&lt;/a&gt; Q2 2018 also found that communication often breaks intergenerational consistency. Employees of all ages bring unique perspectives, life experiences and approaches to their work. Today’s workforce is made up of different generations, and each has different work habits, expectations, and communication styles. Baby Boomers are more akin to handwritten notes while Gen X prefer telephonic or face to face communication. Millennials are more comfortable with emails and Gen Z takes their digital savviness a step further, by using social media and instant messaging more fluently. This also creates a difference in the nature of messaging and the speed of responses. Being aware that there is no one-size-fits-all approach is critical. Organisations therefore are now being more present in all channels – retaining letters but also increasing their presence on social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to look at the positive aspects of working with a multi-generational workforce and overcoming these barriers to seamlessly string together talent. While we are faced with challenges due to the different ways these generations are wired, it opens up several strengths and benefits that can be leveraged. Furthermore, the pandemic triggered changes in the business landscape have created a wider acceptance of a new work order in which age diversity holds a significant part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The foundation of these differences lies in the widely different values held by each generation and the ecosystem they grew up in. Future-ready organisations today are becoming aware of these differences and beginning to create an environment where these four different generations can thrive and complement each other to create a competitive advantage for the business and their own professional growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Despite all the given challenges, it is possible to bring the different generations together and leverage the opportunities that they bring to the workplace. The next blogpost will explore some of the ways in which we can put the different generations together to create a well-oiled machinery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;text-center&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is Part 2 of the Generations Series. Read Part 1 &lt;a href=&quot;/organisation_development/inter-generational-diversity&quot;&gt;Inter-generational Diversity is getting real&lt;/a&gt; and Part 3 &lt;a href=&quot;/organisation_development/making-generational-diversity-work&quot;&gt;Making generational diversity work for you&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Kumar</name></author><category term="Organisation_Development" /><category term="workplace," /><category term="empowerment," /><category term="leadership," /><category term="futureofwork," /><category term="empathy" /><summary type="html">Managing the needs of a diverse workforce that may cover a wide range of generations is a challenge for any organisation. In this second blogpost, I’m taking a closer look at what questions this may pose to organisations and what solutions businesses can consider:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/inter-generational-disruption-post.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/inter-generational-disruption-post.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Making generational diversity work for you</title><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/making-generational-diversity-work" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making generational diversity work for you" /><published>2022-04-12T10:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-04-12T10:30:00+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/making-generational-diversity-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/making-generational-diversity-work">&lt;p&gt;With a multiplicity of generations adding variety, challenge and opportunity to the workplace, the only way businesses can optimise these is by looking at some of the future-looking approaches towards work, culture, career and people practices. Supporting and managing multiple generations of employees can pose a number of challenges for business leaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;text-center&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is Part 3 of the Generations Series. Read Part 1 &lt;a href=&quot;/organisation_development/inter-generational-diversity&quot;&gt;Inter-generational Diversity is getting real&lt;/a&gt; and Part 2 &lt;a href=&quot;/organisation_development/inter-generational-disruption&quot;&gt;The Inter-generational Disruption at workplaces&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While many of these challenges may appear daunting, a multi-generational team also provides an opportunity for people with different perspectives to learn from each other. Let’s look at some of these opportunities and solutions that can help work multi-generational diversity to our advantage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-mentoring-and-knowledge-transfer&quot;&gt;1. Mentoring and knowledge transfer:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the most obvious of all opportunities and it works both ways. While older employees can pass on a lot of information to the younger generation, they can also learn from their younger colleagues. Knowing this, organizations can benefit from a mentoring or advocacy program that also explores the generation gap and educates leaders in effective communication and the strengths of each generation group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developing leaders capable of leading generations of employees is likely to take time, training, and great intergenerational dialogue. As discussed in the previous blogpost, one of the biggest challenges in multigenerational workforce management is getting each generation to recognize and respect the unique attributes of others. It is important to appreciate that differences are related to time, place, and events. Diverse generations can also be considered peers, that is, a group of people who have similar experiences, rather than values due to growing up at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-diversity-and-inclusion&quot;&gt;2. Diversity and Inclusion:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Randstad Work Monitor Q2 2018 identified that 85% of their respondents agree that they come up with innovative ideas and solutions, thanks to an age-diverse team. A huge area of opportunity emerges when different generations interact in a non-judgemental environment with open to healthy questioning and transparent communication. Building a culture of healthy discussions and cross-questioning is an important opportunity that can bring the generations together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not unusual to hear a millennial being described as ‘smart but lacking motivation’, but this could just as well have meant ‘smart but I don’t understand his/her motivation’. Unpacking these motivations is a critical area where immense opportunity resides in dealing with the different generations at the workplace. As discussed in the previous sections, mutual respect and sensitisation towards the different value systems of these generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-constructive-feedback&quot;&gt;3. Constructive feedback:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another sensitive area of opportunity is how feedback is handled between these generations. Closely linked to communication, the organisations can tide over the challenges of misunderstandings by creating a standard system of feedback and building the team capability to give and receive feedback impersonally, timely and clearly. Building sensitisation and awareness in respecting each other’s backstories, value systems, beliefs and world view is important. However, at the same time, it is important to watch out for stereotypes and unconscious biases. It is easy to brush a person with a generation brush and oversee the individual personality traits in absolute terms. This approach can lead to significant loss of opportunity that emerges from having an age-diverse and inclusive work environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-learning-and-talent-management&quot;&gt;4. Learning and talent management:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A progressive career path needs to replace traditional hierarchies with seamless work structures to effectively manage this melting pot of generations. ‘One size fits all’ programs will no longer be valued, and technology will continue to play a pivotal role in this arena. For example, for the Gen Z who are not waiting to complete their education to enter the workplace, e-learning courses and sabbaticals must become built into their career plans. Learning management systems (LMS) to map individual e-learning needs, leveraging digital media to attract and retain the right young talent, and using advanced people management software to track their progression, are just some of the areas where technology can lend an edge to organisations in managing their inter-generational diversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-a-culture-of-trust&quot;&gt;5. A culture of trust:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of change needs to be created on the intangibles as well. The multi-generational workplaces can either turn into war zones or can transform into collaborative, respected centres of excellence that are looked up to in organisations. The latter is possible by only focussing on the strengths of each generation and building trust. It is easier said than done, but once it is revealed to each of the generations that their drives and ambitions are exclusive yet complementing each other, their insecurities can turn into synergies. Extensive coaching to senior employees on handling the younger workers, as well as sensitisation of the millennials to adapt to the older generation is a way forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a classic win-win situation with not only the employees across different generations benefiting from each other but also the organisation progressing. Beyond large savings in attracting and retaining the right talent, the organisations are assured a happy, engaged workforce that is motivated for the right reasons apart from pay. Their employees believe in the vision and work towards improved productivity, which in turn leads to increased customer satisfaction and quality. So, let’s expand the meaning of diversity in our workplaces and blend in all generations together!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;text-center&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is Part 3 of the Generations Series. Read Part 1 &lt;a href=&quot;/organisation_development/inter-generational-diversity&quot;&gt;Inter-generational Diversity is getting real&lt;/a&gt; and Part 2 &lt;a href=&quot;/organisation_development/inter-generational-disruption&quot;&gt;The Inter-generational Disruption at workplaces&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Kumar</name></author><category term="Organisation_Development" /><category term="workplace," /><category term="empowerment," /><category term="leadership," /><category term="futureofwork," /><category term="empathy" /><summary type="html">With a multiplicity of generations adding variety, challenge and opportunity to the workplace, the only way businesses can optimise these is by looking at some of the future-looking approaches towards work, culture, career and people practices. Supporting and managing multiple generations of employees can pose a number of challenges for business leaders.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/making-generational-diversity-work-post.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/making-generational-diversity-work-post.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Inter-generational Diversity is getting real</title><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/inter-generational-diversity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inter-generational Diversity is getting real" /><published>2022-04-07T10:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-04-07T10:30:00+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/inter-generational-diversity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/inter-generational-diversity">&lt;p&gt;The past few months have kept HR folks and business managers amused! Our employees – primarily Millennials and Gen Z – moved out of jobs, sought sky-high pay hikes, and then some started to trickle back to their previous organisations. With this boomerang, the focus has also moved to certain generations at workplace that demonstrated this behaviour more than others. For the first time in modern history, four different generations are at the workplace together. The Baby Boomers have just begun retiring but the other three are still very active in the workplace dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Owing to a greater focus on overall wellness, technological advances in medical sciences and a more active lifestyle of employees, Baby Boomers are retiring later than any of the previous generations did. On the other hand, Gen Z is entering the workforce before any other generation has. They are breaking the traditional moulds of education and are beginning to work even before completing their graduation in the form of internships, secondments or moonlighting assignments. In this three-part blog series, I hope to highlight that managing the needs of this diverse workforce may be challenging, but if handled well, it can help the organisation reap multiple benefits. First, let’s unwrap these four generations and what they bring to workplaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot has been written about the differences between the four generations – their values, beliefs and worldviews. As a construct, ‘generation’ is complex to unravel. As a sociological construct, it has been loosely defined as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“an identifiable group that shares birth years, age, location and significant life events at critical developmental stages”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(- Betty Kupperschmidt, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/12146706_Multigeneration_Employees_Strategies_for_Effective_Management&quot;&gt;Multigeneration Employees: Strategies for Effective Management&lt;/a&gt;, 2000).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generations are largely moulded by historical and economic events too. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fourthturning.com/&quot;&gt;Strauss and Howe&lt;/a&gt; therefore see generations as a cohort of people born within a 20–30-year phase or ‘turnings’. According to them, historical events have repeatedly shaped the values and beliefs of a generational group, which they have categorised into four distinct archetypes – Prophet, Nomad, Hero, and Artist. Together these four archetypes manifest in the form of a &lt;em&gt;saeculum&lt;/em&gt;, roughly over a period of a hundred years – only to be repeated again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When overlayered by regional and cultural differences, the manifestations of a generation differ vastly. For example, the very age brackets of the four generations differs in India from their American counterparts. This is because the events that have triggered a generation to emerge in one country were delayed or deleted in another country. As an example, the Baby Boomers of the U.S. are largely shaped by the post-World War II events and the Cold War disaffections. However, the Indian Baby Boomers grew up in the post-Independence era of constrained resources and opportunities with pre-liberalisation policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, as a culture, India perceives generational diversity at a workplace differently as compared to other societies. Having experienced multi-generational diversity in their personal and social realms, most managers are akin to working with other generations. Indian organisations, therefore, experience different challenges and opportunities as compared to those in low power distance cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Values have a significant role to play within this multigenerational intermingling. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/41683958&quot;&gt;Lyons et al.&lt;/a&gt; defined work values as generalized beliefs about the desirable aspects of work and are known to impact motivation, organizational commitment, decision making, career choice, and organizational citizenship behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://epublications.marquette.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1029&amp;amp;context=cps_professional&quot;&gt;Arsenault and Patrick&lt;/a&gt;, some of the core values associated with each of the first three generational cohorts are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The core values of the Baby Boomers are optimism, personal gratification, and growth. In fact, in the 1970s, the term “workaholic” was coined by &lt;a href=&quot;https://scirp.org/journal/paperinformation.aspx?paperid=91076&quot;&gt;Zemke&lt;/a&gt; to describe the driven work ethic of the Baby Boomers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The core values of Generation X are diversity, techno-literacy, fun, and informality.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The core values of the Millennials are optimism, civic duty, confidence, and achievement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impact of these values transmits to the ways in which they bring themselves to work. Each generation brings with it a different backstory leading from the different value systems and worldview they display. Creating a safe space to share these stories and an open, trusting culture where everyone’s worldview is understood is critical to building an age-diverse environment at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most workplaces, unless consciously wired, these different work styles can lead to tensions and productivity losses. The next blog post in the series looks at some of the challenges faced by organisations when the four generations interact at a single workplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is Part 1 of the Generations Series. Read Part 2 &lt;a href=&quot;/organisation_development/inter-generational-disruption&quot;&gt;Inter-generational Diversity is getting real&lt;/a&gt; and Part 3 &lt;a href=&quot;/organisation_development/making-generational-diversity-work&quot;&gt;Making generational diversity work for you&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Kumar</name></author><category term="Organisation_Development" /><category term="workplace," /><category term="empowerment," /><category term="leadership," /><category term="futureofwork," /><category term="empathy" /><summary type="html">The past few months have kept HR folks and business managers amused! Our employees – primarily Millennials and Gen Z – moved out of jobs, sought sky-high pay hikes, and then some started to trickle back to their previous organisations. With this boomerang, the focus has also moved to certain generations at workplace that demonstrated this behaviour more than others. For the first time in modern history, four different generations are at the workplace together. The Baby Boomers have just begun retiring but the other three are still very active in the workplace dynamics.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/inter-generational-diversity-post.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/inter-generational-diversity-post.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Great Manager Sandwich</title><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/great-manager-sandwich" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Great Manager Sandwich" /><published>2022-04-02T10:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-04-02T10:30:00+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/great-manager-sandwich</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/great-manager-sandwich">&lt;p&gt;The recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/worklab/work-trend-index/great-expectations-making-hybrid-work-work&quot;&gt;Work Trend Index 2022 study&lt;/a&gt; by Microsoft is a great resource for all leaders out there trying to solve the hybrid work puzzle. However, of the five key trends highlighted by the study, the one that really stood out for me personally was that “managers feel wedged between leadership and employee expectations.” A cynic friend laughed when I mentioned this to her – when have managers not felt sandwiched! Alright, so this may not be a new trend but maybe this statistic calls for us to sit up and take notice of the magnitude of the problem – a whopping 54% of managers responded in the study that they felt leadership was out of touch with the employees. What a transition from just a few months ago when Friday coffee chats and virtual town-halls became a go-to guide for leaders to connect with the employees closely. In fact, the leaders were so cued into the frontline challenges and reached out to all employees so often, that the very role of middle-level managers started to get questioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what has changed between the summer of 2021 and the spring of 2022? Indeed, the Great Resignation comes to mind. Also, with two years completed in this new normal, leaders are now keen to bring the focus back to the bottom line and productivity. Employees, on the other hand, have moved on by prioritising their mental health and wellness. In the midst of this, managers could feel stuck trying to balance business results with employee expectations. However, seen differently, it’s a huge opportunity for managers to cement their roles within organisations, as coaches and champions of sustainable engagement. The role of mid-level managers is open to massive disruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Janus – the mythical Roman god of doors and gateways depicted with two opposing faces – the middle-level manager of today has to empathise with both the leadership and the employee in order to unlock opportunities. For those of us walking this critical tight-rope, here are some of the ways that can help us navigate the sticky mid-level sandwich better:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-be-the-champion-coach&quot;&gt;1. Be the champion coach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no more shying away from coaching for managers. I have come across managers who have been great at delivering results and understand their functional expertise perfectly. However, coaching is not about creating clones of oneself, right? It is not about ‘teaching’ someone how to make the perfect sales pitch, for example. It is about helping your team members explore and identify the ‘right’ sales pitch – what works best for them to get results. This calls for deep empathy, simplifying the process of learning, and listening. When managers become coaches, they often share stories of their journey. Storytelling is a great coaching tool, but don’t forget to listen more than you share as a coach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-be-a-key-cultural-anchor&quot;&gt;2. Be a key cultural anchor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that building a strong, single culture is the most important contribution of the managerial layer. As an organisation grows, the leadership gets removed from the front-line employees. In order that the vision of the founders is not diluted by the time it reaches the last mile, the managerial cadre upholds and lives the cultural tenets. Great managers ensure that sub-cultures do not crop up. Every team meeting, every communication, and every process embeds the unspoken organisational culture – and it is the managers who are the custodians of these elements. This role becomes more pronounced in a remote/ hybrid work environment. If an employee feels a disconnect in the spoken and written word versus what they experience in their day-to-day operations, their reasons to move on just add up. Modern managers play a key role in holding together their teams towards a common vision – pandemics and great resignations withstanding!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-be-the-problem-solver&quot;&gt;3. Be the problem solver&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By leveraging their functional expertise along with the line of sight they have of the business, managers are in a unique position to problem solve complex problems. Leaders rely on their managers for ground-level information to make decisions. Critical thinking can help mid-level managers discern the right information that is needed for leadership decision making, as well as the other way around – how to slice and dice the leadership decisions for their teams so it makes actionable sense to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The one common thread that runs between the above three roles is the ability to hold a mirror to both the leadership and the team members. Managers need to get out of their traditional moulds of receiving strategic business plans and transmitting them to their teams. By adding an additional layer of empathy to the plans, they will create immense value for the business and the employees alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Kumar</name></author><category term="Organisation_Development" /><category term="the" /><category term="great" /><category term="resignation," /><category term="empathy," /><category term="manager," /><category term="leadership," /><category term="change" /><summary type="html">The recent Work Trend Index 2022 study by Microsoft is a great resource for all leaders out there trying to solve the hybrid work puzzle. However, of the five key trends highlighted by the study, the one that really stood out for me personally was that “managers feel wedged between leadership and employee expectations.” A cynic friend laughed when I mentioned this to her – when have managers not felt sandwiched! Alright, so this may not be a new trend but maybe this statistic calls for us to sit up and take notice of the magnitude of the problem – a whopping 54% of managers responded in the study that they felt leadership was out of touch with the employees. What a transition from just a few months ago when Friday coffee chats and virtual town-halls became a go-to guide for leaders to connect with the employees closely. In fact, the leaders were so cued into the frontline challenges and reached out to all employees so often, that the very role of middle-level managers started to get questioned.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/man-woman-silhouette-post.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/man-woman-silhouette-post.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Burnout is closing in. Here’s how to keep it at bay</title><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/keep-burnout-at-bay" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Burnout is closing in. Here’s how to keep it at bay" /><published>2022-02-10T10:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-02-10T10:30:00+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/keep-burnout-at-bay</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/keep-burnout-at-bay">&lt;p&gt;While all of us were busy fighting COVID and dealing with variants, vaccinations, and virtual work, a silent epidemic was creeping upon us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recognised by the WHO in 2019 as an “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/news/item/28-05-2019-burn-out-an-occupational-phenomenon-international-classification-of-diseases&quot;&gt;occupational phenomenon&lt;/a&gt;”, ‘burnout’ is the new workplace epidemic that is catching up faster than anything else since March 2020. Workplace stress and feeling professionally deficient were challenges that employees have always faced but what changed with the onset of the pandemic is the intensity and direction. Stress became all-encompassing with uncertainty and job insecurity high during the early days of the pandemic. Subsequently, logging in for endless hours from home, while being monitored and screen-grabbed added to the tensions - both physical and mental. The pandemic jolted us into the realisation that our mental and physical wellbeing was prime. And if I spend eight to ten hours of my waking day at work, my wellbeing is impacted by the nature of work. No doubt then, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/onemind/2021/10/27/prevent-employee-burnout--or-face-the-great-resignation/?sh=1277eb4cb5b2&quot;&gt;many&lt;/a&gt; attribute the Great Resignation to the post-pandemic stress and resultant burnout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations and governments are indeed taking cognizance of these trends and solving for them. However, it doesn’t take away the need to develop our own personal arsenal as well to prevent ourselves from burnout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As social creatures, we need to be in contact with others - not just for our once in a while outings but on an everyday basis. Connecting with others, sharing stories, that post-lunch walk or seemingly unproductive water cooler chat - all lead up to one outcome: shielding us from workplace burnout. Think about it - how many times did you step out for fresh air with a colleague after an exhausting presentation, only to come back refreshed. No amount of efficiency tools, productivity resources, and time management principles can replace that. This emerges from &lt;a href=&quot;https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/business-case-for-empathy&quot;&gt;Empathetic Concern&lt;/a&gt; - which is shared across our work with colleagues and helps us connect to our work in a much more meaningful way. Empathy can emerge to be one of the strongest tools in this battle against burnout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the pandemic nowhere close to relenting and our real water-cooler still distant, can empathy still help us in managing burnout as we continue our virtual routines? I have found the following three fundamental principles truly effective in bringing empathy into our work lives in order to keep burnout at bay:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-set-boundaries&quot;&gt;1. Set boundaries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empathy doesn’t always need to be outward. It is important to be empathetic towards your own needs and make time for self-care. Don’t be a hero and take tighter deadlines than needed or more assignments than you can handle. Reach out for help when needed. Raise flags if projects are going off-track to avoid last-minute stresses. Setting clear boundaries on what you can and cannot do helps set expectations and manage burnout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-build-meaningful-relationships-at-work-and-beyond&quot;&gt;2. Build meaningful relationships at work and beyond&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the surprise of many, it is possible to build a meaningful relationship with colleagues and others, while still at home. For starters, have all your virtual calls with your camera on. Try it for a day and you will feel the difference it has on your mood and overall connect with the person on the other side of the screen. The importance of having team calls beyond work has been talked about so much as well, as has sharing our personal stories, successes and challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-ask-insightful-questions&quot;&gt;3. Ask insightful questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asking the right questions with empathy can help us understand where the other person is coming from. While our own tensions mat seem overwhelming, it is important to step back and see the situation from the other person’s point of view. This is a huge win in beating stress, avoiding unnecessary conflict and inefficiencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These principles can stand in good stead, whether you are working onsite or virtually. Burnout can creep up anytime, anywhere. Let’s bring empathy to work and keep burnout at bay!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Kumar</name></author><category term="Organisation_Development" /><category term="new-beginnings," /><category term="empathy," /><category term="leadership," /><category term="growth" /><summary type="html">While all of us were busy fighting COVID and dealing with variants, vaccinations, and virtual work, a silent epidemic was creeping upon us.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/keep-burnout-at-bay-post.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/keep-burnout-at-bay-post.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Business case for empathy</title><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/business-case-for-empathy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Business case for empathy" /><published>2022-01-10T10:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-01-10T10:30:00+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/business-case-for-empathy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/business-case-for-empathy">&lt;p&gt;A happy new year and welcome to the season of resolutions! Mine is to focus on the positive and continue my practice of gratitude through this year. Searching for positive news though, in these times is definitely not easy, but I did manage to find one yesterday that made me smile. Following the famous New Year’s Ball Drop in New York City this year, Eric Adams took office as the new mayor. One of the key agendas he wants to drive in his team is to hire for more empathy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While organisations and leaders have been talking about empathy for several years, it is heartening to see that the need for more empathetic behaviour is entering into wider areas like public service. In his 2006 book – A Whole New Mind – Daniel Pink spoke about how “the capabilities we once disdained or thought frivolous—the ‘right-brain’ qualities of inventiveness, empathy, joyfulness, and meaning—increasingly will determine who flourishes and who flounders.” Domains like medicine and healthcare, education and law will require us to exhibit greater human skills like empathy and creativity, while letting machines and AI handle what they do best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then again, empathy is considered a soft, mushy half-skill, even a personality trait sometimes – indicating that we either have it in us to be empathetic or don’t. Doubt has loomed on whether empathy can actually be measured. These paradoxes got me started to unpack some questions in my head around modern-age empathy and how it manifests in our work lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-is-empathy-a-skill-or-a-personality-trait&quot;&gt;First, is Empathy a skill or a personality trait?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The construct of empathy became widely known after Daniel Goleman talked about it in his 1995 book on Emotional Intelligence. According to Goleman, empathy is basically the ability to understand others’ emotions and there are three types of empathy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cognitive empathy&lt;/strong&gt; – clearly identified as a ‘skill’ that helps us understand what others are thinking. This skill can indeed be learnt to become better communicators.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emotional empathy&lt;/strong&gt; – observed as an ability to tap into your emotions to build a deeper connection with others.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Empathetic concern&lt;/strong&gt; – also referred to as compassionate empathy, this calls for going beyond feeling the emotions, and acting to help the other person.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As humans, we are wired to feel these emotions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“… the ancient parts of the brain beneath the cortex – the amygdala, the hypothalamus, the hippocampus, and the orbitofrontal cortex – that allow us to feel fast without thinking deeply” enable us to be empathetic at the core.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, like all skills – empathy also needs practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-how-do-i-learn-empathy&quot;&gt;So, how do I learn empathy?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that practicing empathy is actually not that hard. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychologytoday.com/intl/blog/our-social-brains/201007/empathy-101&quot;&gt;Scientists have discovered biological evidence that human brain fires “mirror neurons” when we observe and experience emotion.&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote text-center bg-light&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;Simply put, in order to try to understand what my team member is going through, my brain is capable of pretending that I am going through a similar situation &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to highlight at this point, the difference between empathy and sympathy. Best explained by Dr. Brene Brown in her 2012 book &lt;a href=&quot;https://brenebrown.com/book/daring-greatly/&quot;&gt;Daring Greatly&lt;/a&gt; , empathy makes you vulnerable too. Just pretending to be in a tough spot without a frame of reference will not help build a connect – that is just sympathy. But what if I have never been in that kind of a situation to empathise? As an example, imagine a manager who does not have kids of her own and finds it difficult to connect during a team member’s pregnancy and subsequent maternity period. The situation may sound awkward, but it is very real. The number one tool to build an empathetic connection in such situations is listening. Asking meaningful questions, listening intently and building insights go a long way in enabling empathetic relationships. In brief, you don’t need to have gone through every problem to know how the other person feels. Trust them enough to share their feelings and how they would best use your help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;then-can-the-impact-of-empathy-be-measured&quot;&gt;Then, can the impact of empathy be measured?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of modern research and management studies that point to the fact that empathy in fact is great for business and profitability. Here are three reasons that I could strongly resonate with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-empathy-helps-you-build-greater-customer-connect-and-innovate-in-order-to-build-better-products-and-solve-problems&quot;&gt;1. Empathy helps you build greater customer connect and innovate in order to build better products and solve problems&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding customers’ unmet needs, articulating them and trying to solve those is at the core of a customer-centric, innovative business. In fact, Telefonica Germany implemented a nation-wide &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2015/01/corporate-empathy-is-not-an-oxymoron&quot;&gt;“empathy training program that led to an increase in customer satisfaction of 6% within 6 weeks.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Empathy pays.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-empathetic-leaders-build-bonded-teams-that-are-willing-to-go-over-and-beyond-what-is-defined-in-their-job-descriptions&quot;&gt;2. Empathetic leaders build bonded teams that are willing to go over and beyond what is defined in their job descriptions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaders who communicate with empathy ensure that their team members also feel heard and valued. They build environments where each individual’s strengths are leveraged, and everyone feels fulfilled while working towards a common goal. Further, empathetic leaders care, and true genuine care is the most important currency in today’s uncertain times, when employee needs can vary from safety to mental wellness and everything in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-empathy-makes-for-socially-responsible-businesses-that-care-for-the-ecosystem-they-operate-in-and-define-a-strong-sustainable-journey-for-themselves&quot;&gt;3. Empathy makes for socially responsible businesses that care for the ecosystem they operate in and define a strong sustainable journey for themselves&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses have the power to transcend boundaries and go beyond just economic causes. Leveraging this power needs leaders to be empathetic towards a larger world view and care about the causes that are important. Environment care, diversity and inclusion, climate change, and generating employment are pertinent causes that tie in closely with businesses, allowing them to make a larger difference outside of their balance sheets and build strong brands&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes courage for leaders like Eric Adams to break the mould and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2021/12/18/nyregion/eric-adams-emotional-intelligence.html&quot;&gt;ask for greater empathy in teams and organisations&lt;/a&gt;. It is inspiring to see this change, read the definite research in favour of empathy and celebrate leaders who build businesses with an empathetic concern. Here’s hoping for more empathy in our businesses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Kumar</name></author><category term="Organisation_Development" /><category term="new-beginnings," /><category term="empathy," /><category term="leadership," /><category term="growth" /><summary type="html">A happy new year and welcome to the season of resolutions! Mine is to focus on the positive and continue my practice of gratitude through this year. Searching for positive news though, in these times is definitely not easy, but I did manage to find one yesterday that made me smile. Following the famous New Year’s Ball Drop in New York City this year, Eric Adams took office as the new mayor. One of the key agendas he wants to drive in his team is to hire for more empathy.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/empathy-business-case-post.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/empathy-business-case-post.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The top 3 growth lessons to learn from 2021</title><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/top-3-growth-lessons-of-2021" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The top 3 growth lessons to learn from 2021" /><published>2021-12-21T10:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-12-21T10:30:00+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/top-3-growth-lessons-of-2021</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/top-3-growth-lessons-of-2021">&lt;p&gt;It’s December already! In many ways, I am glad the year went by so quick. What started off with a resurgence of hope and normalcy, quickly turned horrifying, but is finally ending with everyone cautiously making their way into the new normal. ‘New normal’ was the go-to phrase of last year but it is this year that we have truly started to appreciate the meaning of the phrase and its gravity on our lives. Moving on from losses, displaying courage, transcending all differences to help each other, and weaving safety into the fabric of everything we do – the year has taught us many lessons that will stay with us and become our DNA. Here are my top three lessons which will help me navigate towards growth and positivity in the new year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#resilience&quot;&gt;Resilience and the Ability to bounce back &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#innovation&quot;&gt;Innovative Problem-Solving&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#sustainability&quot;&gt;Sustainability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resilience&quot;&gt;1. Resilience &amp;amp; the ability to bounce back&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I start with this lesson because at the core of all of our existence is the ability to collect ourselves from whatever we have been through and move on. Psychologist and author &lt;a href=&quot;https://angeladuckworth.com/&quot;&gt;Angela Duckworth&lt;/a&gt; indicates Resilience as the ability to bounce back after we have struggled or failed. The key to resilience is often being able to see across the darkness and just know that there is light. No one will tell you that. It comes from deep-seated optimism, faith and self-awareness. It also needs us to be gritty – to never give up trying to work towards a better tomorrow. In many ways, this is the most important milestone as we chart our road towards growth and building a better tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;innovation&quot;&gt;2. Innovative Problem Solving&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am probably cheating a little here by clubbing two critical lessons into one! However, in my defence, this year has pushed our limits to try and solve problems we never knew existed. Vaccinating your workforce was never part of any organisational job description. With businesses returning to normalcy during the first half of the year, so many of us innovated to make sure each one of their employees – no matter how remote – was safely vaccinated. This is just one example that I’m sure resonates with many of us. Several other such case studies have proven that a straight-jacketed approach to work will not work in the future. Boundaries will have to be redefined and problems will need to be seen from an innovative lens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sustainability&quot;&gt;3. Sustainability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lesson is closest to me – personally and professionally. When we started out, at Samriddhi Consulting, we made a conscious decision to choose sustainable growth projects that were meaningful and had a long-term impact on the business. However, the post-pandemic appreciation of our environment had a deeper personal impact on me. I started seriously reading up about Sustainability and realised that it is not the same as ‘environmental-ism’! Sustainability is defined by the United Nations as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote text-center bg-light&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;development that meets the needs of the present without compromising the ability of future generations to meet their own needs&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sustainabledevelopment.un.org/content/documents/5987our-common-future.pdf&quot;&gt;The United Nations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can work across the entire spectrum of activities we are involved in – social and economic. For the longest time, we were limited by our thinking that this balance is unachievable, but sometimes a jolt is needed to make us realise that what we have been taking for granted isn’t possible anymore. Work from home proved that we could reduce our carbon footprint by travelling less. 2021 has been the year when #netzero and EarthShot became forces of action towards preserving our climate. The scarcity of fuel in Britain this year was another bolt for us to consider electric vehicles seriously. Several &lt;a href=&quot;https://interestingengineering.com/21-sustainability-innovations-that-might-just-change-the-world&quot;&gt;start-ups&lt;/a&gt; are successfully and profitably engaging in responsible businesses to create a better future. My personal commitment this year has been to reduce my carbon footprint and I started by measuring mine &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.org/en-us/get-involved/how-to-help/carbon-footprint-calculator/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. As a vegetarian, who doesn’t drive around much now, I was disappointed to find out that my carbon footprint is 5.49 tonnes of CO2e as against the global average of 4 tonnes per year. But as we say, the journey towards improvement begins with measuring!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On that note, I’m looking forward to a year when I can be conscious about my personal impact on this planet and reduce to at least 4 tonnes of CO2e by next time this year and use my resilience and innovation to get there. So much for public commitments 😊 Here’s wishing all of you a wonderful festive season as well and best wishes as we ring in a new year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Kumar</name></author><category term="Organisation_Development" /><category term="new-normal," /><category term="growth," /><category term="learning," /><category term="innovation," /><category term="sustainability" /><summary type="html">It’s December already! In many ways, I am glad the year went by so quick. What started off with a resurgence of hope and normalcy, quickly turned horrifying, but is finally ending with everyone cautiously making their way into the new normal. ‘New normal’ was the go-to phrase of last year but it is this year that we have truly started to appreciate the meaning of the phrase and its gravity on our lives. Moving on from losses, displaying courage, transcending all differences to help each other, and weaving safety into the fabric of everything we do – the year has taught us many lessons that will stay with us and become our DNA. Here are my top three lessons which will help me navigate towards growth and positivity in the new year:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/2021-growth-lessons-post.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/2021-growth-lessons-post.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The debate about returning to the office</title><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/return-to-office" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The debate about returning to the office" /><published>2021-10-29T10:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-10-29T10:30:00+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/return-to-office</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/organisation_development/return-to-office">&lt;p&gt;Since March 2020, organisations have been caught in a mass-scale social experiment, never seen before, never imagined! Last year, every organisation went into a massive work from home experiment, overnight. Most were unprepared and several took months to adjust. Sixteen months on, with most of us double vaccinated, the question that looms in our minds now is - whether to return to office or not. Organisational pundits have predicted a hybrid model - one that can work in a few different ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before deciding what is the best ‘return-to-work’ strategy for a particular organisation, there are several factors that need to be considered – some tangible (like productivity, cost, and employee preferences) while others not so tangible (like impact on innovation and collaboration). Let’s look at it from a three-fold perspective:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#how&quot;&gt;How work is delivered in your organisation?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#where&quot;&gt;Where are your business’ touchpoints?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#who&quot;&gt;Who is your mission-critical talent and what inspires them?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how&quot;&gt;1. How work is delivered in your organisation?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deconstruct your business model and take a bold look at which pieces can be digitised or have already been automated. The pandemic has forced most organisations to adopt a digital-first approach. If most of your suppliers, employees, and customers are technologically enabled and connected, the advantage offered by a return-to-office approach is limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having said that, digitised organisations too have a need to unplug and come face-to-face. If your business model is based on intense and ongoing research, innovation, and team brainstorming, the need for these teams to come together occasionally and safely must be catered to within your return-to-work strategy. Whether this is through periodic team meetings or a quarterly retreat – options abound!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important factor to consider here is the organisation culture. Organisation cultures, like people’s personalities, are unique and often intangible. This is where you need to have maximum conversation with team leaders and listen intently to your employees. Does your organisation display the resilience and agility needed when working remotely? Are your leaders equipped to uphold the organisation’s culture without traditional levers like face-to-face town halls or physical meetings?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reimagine your work across all functions from the lens of digitalisation, automation, culture, and adaptability to narrow down to the right mix of in-person time your teams need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where&quot;&gt;2. Where are your business’ touchpoints?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The location of your current business points of contact will have a huge impact on what kind of hybrid model you want to adopt. The approach will vary widely for an organisation that has multiple retail outlets versus one from a core manufacturing sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another factor to be considered here is how your workplace supports and enables productivity. Most organisations have reported that their employees are more productive while working from home. However, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/publication/the-effects-of-remote-work-on-collaboration-among-information-workers/&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; of 61000 Microsoft employees revealed that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote text-center bg-light&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;while productivity rose during remote work, collaboration became “more static and siloed”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/publication/the-effects-of-remote-work-on-collaboration-among-information-workers/&quot;&gt;The effects of remote work on collaboration among information workers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations need to identify their primary channels of communication – formal and informal, internal and external – and these channels ought to cover both work and non-work aspects like organisational engagement and team bonding. Some teams are immensely comfortable bonding over Slack or Teams chat while others lose tacit knowledge if they don’t meet at the water cooler. Where these conversations take place within your organisations is critical to identify and feed into your return-to-work policy too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who&quot;&gt;3. Who is your mission-critical talent and what inspires them?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main reasons organisations are rethinking the ‘how’ and ‘where’ of work in the future is because a significant population of their workforce wants to keep the flexibility. In fact, according to one EY survey,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote text-center bg-light&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;more than half of employees globally would quit their jobs if not provided post-pandemic flexibility &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ey.com/en_gl/news/2021/05/more-than-half-of-employees-globally-would-quit-their-jobs-if-not-provided-post-pandemic-flexibility-ey-survey-finds&quot;&gt;2021 EY Work Reimagined Employee Survey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this talent that you will lose from return-to-work policies is easily replaceable, the answer is clear. On the flip side, is your mission-critical hard to find where your physical offices are located? Or, have you been trying to drive an inclusion and diversity agenda for years with no luck? This is the time for you to bolster your talent strategy – make it agile and inclusive. You no longer need to be limited to one city, state, or country to find the right talent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, consider the capabilities of your team leaders and managers. How does your organisation develop talent? Is coaching a structured intervention within the organisation or do managers like to mentor their teams over a face-to-face meeting?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not the least, consider role definitions and how can the talent be built to fill those roles. For fully remote roles and hybrid roles, talent sourcing is easier but you may need to invest more behind upskilling. However, roles that are fully on-site or hybrid by exception need more investment behind talent access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Blending in-office and remote workers present organisations with new challenges. As this future of work faces us, we need to look at the larger purpose of offices and how they enable organisations and teams to support their unique cultures and brand personalities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Kumar</name></author><category term="Organisation_Development" /><category term="return" /><category term="to" /><category term="work," /><category term="organisation" /><category term="design," /><category term="new-normal," /><category term="strategy," /><category term="remote" /><category term="work" /><summary type="html">Since March 2020, organisations have been caught in a mass-scale social experiment, never seen before, never imagined! Last year, every organisation went into a massive work from home experiment, overnight. Most were unprepared and several took months to adjust. Sixteen months on, with most of us double vaccinated, the question that looms in our minds now is - whether to return to office or not. Organisational pundits have predicted a hybrid model - one that can work in a few different ways.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/return-to-work-post.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/return-to-work-post.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Unravelling Decision Fatigue and how to avoid it</title><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/decision-fatigue" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unravelling Decision Fatigue and how to avoid it" /><published>2021-10-01T10:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-10-01T10:30:00+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/decision-fatigue</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/decision-fatigue">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Is a cotton mask better than an N95 mask?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Should we buy a face shield?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Can we have friends over for a tea?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Which sanitiser is safest for our family?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past sixteen months have thrown a myriad of decisions at us – most that were unused to or had no precedent to refer to for. Add to it the ever-changing information we received every day about the virus and how to deal with it. This overload of information weighed down on our minds, clouding our decision-making abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Known as &lt;strong&gt;decision fatigue&lt;/strong&gt;, this strain on our decision-making faculties is due to mental exhaustion or being forced to go through multiple complex choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-decision-fatigue-real&quot;&gt;Is decision fatigue real?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt – decision fatigue is a real threat in this post-pandemic new normal. It’s not a new phenomenon, however. We have heard of leaders and businesspeople dressing up in similar outfits to avoid the need to make complex styling decisions every morning. Barack Obama and Mark Zuckerberg being the classic and oft-quoted examples here. The key psychological concept here being that by freeing up the brain from taking redundant or repetitive decisions, the brain can focus its decision-making capabilities on more complex circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decision making by itself, even on the best of days, is a tough skill to master. In these unprecedented circumstances, it becomes more depleted because we have no experience of taking these new decisions. What, then, is the impact on us and our decision making when faced with this barrage of questions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decision fatigue is not just a feeling of tiredness. It has a real impact on our physiology and the outcomes of our decisions. According to one study,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote text-center bg-light&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;chess grandmasters often burn up to 6,000 calories per day when participating in high-level tournaments due to the intense stress of the strategic decisions they’re making. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fastcompany.com/90677496/one-unlikely-culprit-to-burnout-youre-lack-of-laziness&quot;&gt;Why a lack of lazy behavior is increasing your burnout (fastcompany.com)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Increased brain activity is indeed a real drain on energy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, research also shows that decision fatigue affects the part of the brain associated with cognition and self-control. This implies that decision fatigue can, on the one hand, cause us to take impulse actions (like binge eating or shopping) and on the other hand, get us into analysis paralysis (like delaying important decisions). Being at either end of this spectrum can be a risky proposition and lead to poor decision outcomes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-avoid-decision-fatigue&quot;&gt;How to avoid decision fatigue?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that so many months into the pandemic, it is now possible to take control of our lives and the decisions around them, to a large extent. Some proven ways to avoid decision fatigue are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-self-awareness&quot;&gt;1. Self-awareness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing what the source of your decision fatigue is and how your brain is responding to it is the first step in helping yourself avoid it. Understand your cognitive waves like the time of the day when you take your best decisions. Flow with your natural energy instead of trying to cram your day with activities as they come. For example, as a morning person, I never leave critical decisions till the end of the day. I know they will get my depleted mind share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-simplify-or-automate-choices&quot;&gt;2. Simplify or automate choices&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learn from Obama and Zuckerberg! Clothes is an easy decision to automate. I also like to automate grocery shopping, menu planning for the week and other such mundane decisions which drain my energy otherwise. The idea is simple - pick your battles!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-have-an-ally&quot;&gt;3. Have an ally&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decision fatigue affects all of us. Rely on your allies to help you through the low stretch and vice versa. Enlist close friends and family members to flag off poor decisions when you are fatigued. Also, try delegating decisions where stakes are lower for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burnout is the enemy of good decision making. Just as self-care and health have become important parts of the modern productivity toolkit, decision strength is an element that can no longer be ignored.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Kumar</name></author><category term="Instructional_Design" /><category term="decision" /><category term="fatigue," /><category term="productivity," /><category term="new-normal," /><category term="burnout," /><category term="decision" /><category term="making" /><summary type="html">Is a cotton mask better than an N95 mask?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/decision-fatigue-post.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/decision-fatigue-post.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why is my Online Training not effective?</title><link href="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/online-training-effectiveness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why is my Online Training not effective?" /><published>2021-09-20T10:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-09-20T10:30:00+05:30</updated><id>https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/online-training-effectiveness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/instructional_design/online-training-effectiveness">&lt;p&gt;You may ask that you have tried everything from using breakout rooms to online quizzes and fun videos to engage your learners. Why then do your learners still sit with their audio and video muted in the v-ILT sessions? Why are the learning completion metrics on your LMS still low? Why do you still have to follow up with learners to log-in and complete their learning?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer these questions, I would step back to the fundamentals of instructional design. The first step is called Training Needs Assessment (TNA). It may seem like an extremely simple place to start from, but I cannot over emphasize the importance of a good need assessment because it forms the very backbone of your program. TNA is often under-rated or limited to subjective discussion-based tools. Poor understanding of the learning objectives will inadvertently lead to poor effectiveness of the program delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;form action=&quot;https://formspree.io/f/mrgrjaoo&quot; method=&quot;POST&quot; class=&quot;card ml-4 d-none d-lg-inline-block float-lg-right&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 400px&quot;&gt;
  &lt;h3 class=&quot;card-header text-center&quot;&gt;
    Get a copy of Samriddhi TNA diagnostic tool
  &lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post550.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; media=&quot;(max-width:550px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post750.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; media=&quot;(max-width:750px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; media=&quot;(min-width:751px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post550.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; media=&quot;(max-width:550px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post750.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; media=&quot;(max-width:750px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width:751px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post.jpg&quot; style=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;card-img-top&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;card-body&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;form-group&quot;&gt;
        &lt;label for=&quot;inputEmail&quot;&gt;Email address&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;email&quot; name=&quot;email&quot; class=&quot;form-control&quot; id=&quot;inputEmail&quot; aria-describedby=&quot;emailHelp&quot; required=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;small id=&quot;emailHelp&quot; class=&quot;form-text text-muted&quot;&gt;We'll never share your email with anyone else.&lt;/small&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;form-group&quot;&gt;
        &lt;label for=&quot;fullName&quot;&gt;Full Name&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;text&quot; class=&quot;form-control&quot; id=&quot;fullName&quot; name=&quot;fullName&quot; required=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;Samriddhi Consulting is committed to protecting and respecting your privacy, and we’ll only use your personal information to administer your account and to provide the products and services you requested from us. In order to provide you the content requested, we need to store and process your personal data. If you consent to us storing your personal data for this purpose, please tick the checkbox below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;form-group form-check&quot;&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;form-check-input&quot; id=&quot;emailConsent&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;label class=&quot;form-check-label small&quot; for=&quot;emailConsent&quot; name=&quot;emailConsent&quot;&gt;Please send me the tool by email&lt;/label&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;card-footer&quot;&gt;
    &lt;button type=&quot;submit&quot; class=&quot;btn btn-primary d-block mx-auto&quot;&gt;Submit&lt;/button&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may not seem like but validating learning outcomes through a detailed need assessment is in fact the less time-consuming step, as compared to what follows! This is also because at Samriddhi, we have template-ised this crucial step, so you never miss out the finer details in conducting your TNA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;d-lg-none btn btn-outline-secondary&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#tna-form&quot;&gt;Click here to get a copy of the Samriddhi TNA Diagnostic Tool&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step after TNA is what causes most of us maximum discomfort – discerning which category your learning outcomes fall into:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knowledge dissemination, or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Skill building.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is sometimes possible to confuse between these two. Consider a training on negotiation skills – do you want your learners to understand the process of negotiation? Or do you want them to develop their own style, practice it and apply it in work situations? Now who doesn’t want the latter, right? But are we then ready to commit ourselves to achieving that learning outcome? Hence it is important to understand the trade-offs between choosing between the &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;skill&lt;/em&gt; buckets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason this is important is because &lt;em&gt;sticky&lt;/em&gt; learning is only achieved when we treat learning as a process, and not as an event. So, while an information dissemination training can fall into the first bucket and be an isolated learning event, application of skills or behaviours to workplace situations, needs significant time and effort. It is this stickiness that makes the online training truly effective and is therefore brings in the concept of &lt;em&gt;performance support&lt;/em&gt; in learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Performance-supported learning answers one question: “How does my learning program enhance the performance of my learners?” And because it is such a bottom-line driven question, measuring the effectiveness of the online training is built into the program design from a very early stage.
Consider a simple example. If a learner scores high scores on all knowledge quizzes in the program, would that count towards program effectiveness? Not so much, right? However, if the learner demonstrates that she/he can apply the learning in real life situations, the program be considered effective. The idea is to replicate the learning environment as closely as possible to the actual workplace and introduce key concepts by linking them to the learners’ pre-existing knowledge, skill or behaviour patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is what makes performance-supported learning so interesting too. It offers endless opportunities to innovate on the content, experiment with varied instructional design tools and incorporate relevant workplace-linked assessments. Some different instructional design tools we have used in the recent past are scenario-based tests, job aids, video tutorial, system simulation, feedback-based role plays, etc. These are called learning scaffolding, which supports the learner as s/he walks through the process of picking up the new skill. With subsequent steps in the learning journey, we reduce the scaffolding, giving greater confidence to the learner to apply the skills in real-life scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To summarise, make sure to run a strong training needs analysis before designing your program and use performance-supported learning to make your online programs more effective. We would love to hear more from you about your experiences and challenges in making online training effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;form action=&quot;https://formspree.io/f/mrgrjaoo&quot; method=&quot;POST&quot; class=&quot;card d-lg-none&quot; id=&quot;tna-form&quot;&gt;
  &lt;h3 class=&quot;card-header text-center&quot;&gt;
    Get a copy of Samriddhi TNA diagnostic tool
  &lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post550.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; media=&quot;(max-width:550px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post750.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; media=&quot;(max-width:750px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post.webp&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; media=&quot;(min-width:751px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post550.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; media=&quot;(max-width:550px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post750.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; media=&quot;(max-width:750px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width:751px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/simplifying-training-needs-analysis-post.jpg&quot; style=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;card-img-top&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;card-body&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;form-group&quot;&gt;
        &lt;label for=&quot;inputEmail&quot;&gt;Email address&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;email&quot; name=&quot;email&quot; class=&quot;form-control&quot; id=&quot;inputEmail&quot; aria-describedby=&quot;emailHelp&quot; required=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;small id=&quot;emailHelp&quot; class=&quot;form-text text-muted&quot;&gt;We'll never share your email with anyone else.&lt;/small&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;form-group&quot;&gt;
        &lt;label for=&quot;fullName&quot;&gt;Full Name&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;text&quot; class=&quot;form-control&quot; id=&quot;fullName&quot; name=&quot;fullName&quot; required=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;Samriddhi Consulting is committed to protecting and respecting your privacy, and we’ll only use your personal information to administer your account and to provide the products and services you requested from us. In order to provide you the content requested, we need to store and process your personal data. If you consent to us storing your personal data for this purpose, please tick the checkbox below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;form-group form-check&quot;&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;form-check-input&quot; id=&quot;emailConsent&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;label class=&quot;form-check-label small&quot; for=&quot;emailConsent&quot; name=&quot;emailConsent&quot;&gt;Please send me the tool by email&lt;/label&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;card-footer&quot;&gt;
    &lt;button type=&quot;submit&quot; class=&quot;btn btn-primary d-block mx-auto&quot;&gt;Submit&lt;/button&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Kumar</name></author><category term="Instructional_Design" /><category term="learning," /><category term="training" /><category term="need" /><category term="analysis," /><category term="training" /><category term="effectiveness," /><category term="training" /><category term="retention," /><category term="performance" /><summary type="html">You may ask that you have tried everything from using breakout rooms to online quizzes and fun videos to engage your learners. Why then do your learners still sit with their audio and video muted in the v-ILT sessions? Why are the learning completion metrics on your LMS still low? Why do you still have to follow up with learners to log-in and complete their learning?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/online-training-support-post.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://samriddhiconsulting.com/assets/images/online-training-support-post.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>